<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Project L</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2016-03-20T17:59:54+02:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Odysseas Lamtzidis</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>odyslam@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry pi 2]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/rpi-post/" />
  <id>/rpi-post</id>
  <updated>2016-04-21T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-03-21T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Odysseas Lamtzidis</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>odyslam@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;raspberry-pi-2&quot;&gt;Raspberry pi 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rpilogo.png&quot; alt=&quot;logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you propably arleady know, Rpi is a small computer running a version of linux called Debian.Although it can run several more version of linux, including custom ones that are made for specific purposes (i.e Voice Control) or Windows 10, Debian is by far the most common and versatile one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s setup is fairly easy thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/help/noobs-setup/&quot;&gt;Noob Setup&lt;/a&gt; and you can get it up and running in no time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro-Tip&lt;/strong&gt;
It’s important that after you setup it and connect it to the internet(via cable or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/configuration/wireless/wireless-cli.md&quot;&gt;wi-fi dongle&lt;/a&gt;), you configure &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/remote-access/ssh/&quot;&gt;ssh&lt;/a&gt; so you gain access to it’s command line remotely, through OS X terminal, linux command line or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/remote-access/ssh/windows.md&quot;&gt;ssh client&lt;/a&gt; for windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now that..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://49.media.tumblr.com/6719493c95b322c8373afb6ccef98e23/tumblr_n8os443A2Q1sl21koo1_500.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://49.media.tumblr.com/6719493c95b322c8373afb6ccef98e23/tumblr_n8os443A2Q1sl21koo1_500.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s continue with what makes Raspberry Pi so special. It houses a wealth of hardware for a fairly limited price. It ranges from a camera display to the most important piece, the 40 GPIO pins that transform rpi from a simple micro-computer to a versatile controler of electronic components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 USB ports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;40 GPIO pins&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Full HDMI port&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ethernet port&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined 3.5mm audio jack and composite video&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Camera interface (CSI)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Display interface (DSI)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Micro SD card slot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VideoCore IV 3D graphics core&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to explain more at this point as it’s better to explain the various capabilities with examples from my project. It’s worth though to display  the pinout diagram as it’s very important for any project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.toptechboy.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/raspberry-pi-2-pinout.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.toptechboy.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/raspberry-pi-2-pinout.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.toptechboy.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/06/raspberry-pi-2-pinout.jpg&quot; title=&quot;GPIO Pinout&quot;&gt;GPIO Pinout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;but-what-are-those-pesky--gpio-anyhow&quot;&gt;But what are those pesky  GPIO anyhow?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a fair question, GPIO stands for “General Purpose Input Output” meaning that these pins can be used as digital inputs or digital outputs. There are also pins that act as power supply(providing either 5v or 3.3v) or as ground. Some GPIO also have special functions (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.sparkfun.com/tutorials/pulse-width-modulation&quot;&gt;pulse width modulation&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;notice&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REMEMBER&lt;/strong&gt;: Rpi use 3.3v as logical 1 and 0v as logical 0, unlike other microcontrolers,like &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; which use 5v.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gpio-control&quot;&gt;GPIO control?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you propably have guess arleady, gpio can be controlled through scripts in various languages that use specific libraries that do most of the dirty work. My personal favorite is python as it’s easily understandable and ridiculously versatile and for these reason our main focus will be python.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;thats-all-folks&quot;&gt;That’s all folks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that you have the all the neaded material to understand the rudimentary level of my project, next will follow an overview of the project and slowly we will start geting into the software side of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rpi-post/&quot;&gt;Raspberry pi 2&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Odysseas Lamtzidis at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Project L&lt;/a&gt; on March 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Project]]></title>
 <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/the-project-post/" />
  <id>/the-project-post</id>
  <updated>2016-04-20T00:00:00-00:00</updated>
  <published>2016-03-20T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  
  <author>
    <name>Odysseas Lamtzidis</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>odyslam@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;The Idea&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All started when I wanted to start exploring the world of electronics, which afterall is one of the subjects of my studies. Moreoever I wanted to start a usable project, something that would not only be &lt;em&gt;educative&lt;/em&gt;, but also &lt;em&gt;usefull&lt;/em&gt; . I also found IoT quite fancinating, something that is going to dominate the technology market in the next few decafed allong with-or in conjuction with - VR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was starting from absolute 0, so &lt;em&gt;Arduino&lt;/em&gt; was the obvious choice because of it’s easy and straight-forward approach. The project did not evolve much as Arduino is fairly limited, especially if you want web capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, &lt;em&gt;Raspberry&lt;/em&gt; creeped in and suddenly everything turned green and shiny. It was able to do what I wanted and the best part? it’s codable in python, one of the easiest and most versatile programming languages I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-is-that-fracking-project&quot;&gt;So what is that fracking project?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said it’s IoT related and more specifically in the area of smart-home. I have automated some tasks, like locking and unlocking my door, and I plan to add many features, all controlled via a Web Interface.I plan to explaing everything I have done in detail, and I hope that it serves as an easy guide for starters in order to dwelve into both the world of IoT and the world of Raspberry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the next posts I will &lt;em&gt;explain&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1)What I have accomplished thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2)What software I use, libraries and scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3)What’s my hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4)Future plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;sonow-what&quot;&gt;So..now what?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is currently frozen at ver 0.1 as I want to bring the blog up to date and then continue with it. At the next blog I will btiefly explain raspberry pi, just to make sure we are at the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then, cheers!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/the-project-post/&quot;&gt;The Project&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Odysseas Lamtzidis at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Project L&lt;/a&gt; on March 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
