<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blog.py</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://odyslam.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 21:56:53 +0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 21:56:53 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Philosophy: Index</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/4mBUYZN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cover photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an index of all the blog posts that talk about the book “What is Philosophy”, by Jose Ortega y Gaset. You can find here a link to the blog posts that review every chapter, as also the core concepts and important questions that I had after reading every chapter. Finally, we compile a list of all the people and books he mentions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapters&quot;&gt;Chapters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 1 :
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/what-is-philosophy-chapter-1&quot;&gt;Review post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#chapter-1&quot;&gt;Interesting concepts, Important Questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-1&quot;&gt;Chapter 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interesting-concepts&quot;&gt;Interesting concepts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The differentiation between ideas and thoughts is very enticing, between men who think and the object of thought. Even though a particular society may support an idea for a point in history, that doesn’t mean that the idea will then die. It will simply be forgotten, only to be rediscovered later on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ortega doesn’t seem to have a strong opinion on why certain men came up with certain ideas at a certain period of time. He seems to rather of-load the task to historians. Personally, being a child of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nntaleb&quot;&gt;Nassim Nicholas Taleb&lt;/a&gt;, I believe that luck plays a more important role than we like to admit. In my view, although there are certain realities that must be taken into account, such as the progressive nature of technology or the societal realities of every historical period, luck is a major player. Newton might just be the only person who thought about it and was in a position to pursue his interest and share his thoughts. Perhaps the one other person who arrived at a relevant conclusion was killed by the plague, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Plague_of_London&quot;&gt;rampant at that time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The world is far more chaotic than we can model, being in mathematical equations or historical analysis. What we can’t model, we simply call it luck.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The writing style of the book is a pleasant surprise. Staying true to the promise of a lecture, it is palpable that the writer is talking to someone, a discussion between a great teacher and a pupil. Not as dry as one would expect from a philosophical book, it employs literally tools to keep the reader hooked on the “story”. Even the ending of the chapter has a cliff-hanger aesthetic, prompting you to think “and then?!”, as you hurry up to the next chapter to find out the rest of the story. It is worth noting that it’s a challenging task to talk about complex subjects in a way that they are digestible from the general public.  A fine line between being epistemologically accurate, but simple. Personally, I would note here &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yuval_Noah_Harari&quot;&gt;Yuval Noah Harari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman&quot;&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/a&gt; as two teachers who have managed to succeed in simplifying accurately their domains for public consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I feel that there is a connection between the super-real nature of the ideas and the view of the Ancient Greeks about the Gods. They are superhuman beings, but with relatable human characteristics, as the descent from Mount Olympus for every kind of mischief. Respectively, ideas descent every now and then from the plane, atemporal beings but in a temporal form. Just like Zeus, who would descend and take the shape of animals in order to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Europa_(consort_of_Zeus)&quot;&gt;court with mortal women&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;important-questions&quot;&gt;Important Questions:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have concluded that there is a connection between people and the ideas that they discover. What is that connection and how much of it is luck?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schlegel argues that “we have a genius for the things that we like”. Ortega seems to say something similar, that man’s derive pleasure when realizing his own destiny. Is this true or wishful thinking? And if it is true, can we généralise that: If we do what we love, we will do it so well, that the society will want to reward us for the value that we produce”. If there was a time that this was true, that is now, given the “permission-less leverage” of the Internet and the rise of the creator economy.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Relevant thinkers in the space are:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shl&quot;&gt;Sahil Lavingia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/naval&quot;&gt;Naval Ravikant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jackbutcher&quot;&gt;Jack Butcher&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/david_perell&quot;&gt;David Perell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people--external-resources&quot;&gt;People &amp;amp; External Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%C3%A9_Descartes&quot;&gt;Descartes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plato&quot;&gt;Plato&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_forms&quot;&gt;Origin of ideas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac_Newton&quot;&gt;Newton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedrich_Schlegel&quot;&gt;Schlegel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-index/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-index/</guid>
        
        <category>2021</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Ortega</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Philosophy: chapter 1</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/9yhCTql.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;philosophy-today-the-strange-adventure-which-befalls-truths-the-coming-of-the-truth-articulation-of-history-with-philosophy&quot;&gt;Philosophy Today. The strange Adventure which befalls Truths: The coming of the Truth. Articulation of History with Philosophy.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ortega starts with an aphorism, stating that in matters of love, art and ideas, there is no value in announcements. If you reflect on these, you will be set apart from others, unaffected by their opinion, as you begin an internal and personal journey. An announced idea “a thought that is separated from the mental road that leads toward it”, is like an island in the middle of the pacific, barren and with no real value. Instead, he prefers to take us from the start, as he did himself before, a journey that is our responsibility to see to the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophy, at the time of writing(or rather speaking, since this is actually a lecture) which is around 1930, has seen a recent uptake in the public interest. A renewed interest because people have started to feel a new need for ideas which in turn is translated into a renewed sense of joy or “voluptuous pleasure”. As we will later see, internal needs are accompanied by the pleasure of the senses “voluptuous pleasure is the face that happiness wears”. We are happy when we realize ourselves, we fulfill our destiny, “when we are being that which in truth we are”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We have a genius for what we like” - Schlegel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this era with a “philosophical destiny”, we will start by stating why we approach philosophy differently than in the previous era, which was quite the opposite for philosophers.  As Ortega underlines, we will move in circles, not a straight line. The radius of the circles will progressively reduce, as we approach the center, our goal.“The great philosophical problems demand a tactic like the Hebrews followed to take Jericho: No direct attack, circling slowly around them and tightening the curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will start from the abstracts, the foundations and as we move forward, we will discuss more everyday issues, how philosophy can be tied back to our own beings. “ We are going to decent boldly below what each one customarily thinks his life to be”. Although we will be scientific in our demeanor, “clarity is the form of courtesy that the philosopher owns”, thus no jargon will be used, like in other sciences. Jargon, that great dragon that guards his treasures, will not be present here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We initiated our discourse by stating that this era is a better one for philosophers, a different kind of philosophy. This is like saying that truth can change, the truth of yesterday and is longer applicable today and vice-versa. But the truth can’t change, truth is elemental. An idea can’t change, but the thought is only human. We may forget or rediscover an idea, but we can’t create or destroy it. As Plato put it, ideas live in a place that is above temporal, in a &lt;strong&gt;supercelestial region&lt;/strong&gt;, above time and space. Sometimes, these ideas, filter down from that place out of space and time into our mortal world, they come as thoughts. When we forget them, they simply return to their rightful place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting analogy that we may use here is energy: It can’t be created or be destroyed, only change form. Ideas, respectively,  can’t be created or destroyed, only discovered and forgotten. Let’s pause a bit on this and think about it. Ideas don’t die, thoughts do. We may forget gravity, but that doesn’t mean that it doesn’t exist or it didn’t exist before Newton had the thought of gravity. 2 + 2 will always make 4, whether we acknowledge it or not. To that effect, we can say that ideas are not &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&quot;&gt;Lindy&lt;/a&gt; compatible, because they are eternal. Thoughts, on the other hand, thoughts live and die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; Lindy compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been reading the Ancients quite a bit and every time I am astonished at how pertinent they are. They are speaking about ideas that concern human nature, and those ideas are eternal. It’s no luck that modern literature is simply rehashing principles dictated more than 2000 years ago. We are simply re-discovering them. An argument could be made that human society has changed little over the course of the centuries, at least in principles. Indeed, you can find the comments of Seneca about the psyche of busy senators to be apt descriptions of the archetype businessman of the western civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are temporal beings, we come and go. We are dust in the wind. Ideas are atemporal.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/4mdmZlo.png&quot; alt=&quot;ideas are atemporal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question arises, almost naturally, why do certain people think about certain ideas at a certain period of time? Is there an affinity between Newton and the law of gravitation and if so, what is the relationship between the thought and the object of that thought, the law itself that is. Although Ortega clearly differentiates between the thought and the idea, he mentions that history, as a science, should aspire to answer the previous question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ortega here gives his first aphorism, saying that the thought has nothing to do with the object or idea that is the kernel of the thought. When we think about the Himalayas, he argues, we can conceive neither its characteristics nor the scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truths, ideas, they do not change. It is men who change, and as we pass through the centuries, we alter our view of the world, our ethics, altering the ideas that we hold dear. Ideas that fall out of place, do not lose value, because if they are true, they remain true. It’s us that we lose sight until the next generations rediscover what we discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this whole discourse has value really should we agree that the man is indeed a rational being. The ancient and the medieval world seem to arrive at this conclusion. So when history goes to study society, from the primitive times until now, it assumes that there is a reason why men act the way they do. This is a basic assumption, as there wouldn’t be any value in analyzing our history, should we agreed that it was a sum of random activities.  Descartes believed that humans are purely rational, incapable of variation, thus history is about the inhuman deviations of men. A log of a series of mistakes and tragic events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We end this chapter with an enigmatic observation by Ortega, that the 19th century had been a time very negative for philosophy, which was bent to an absolute minimum in the minds of people. If it could be abolished, he says, it would have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see why on the following chapter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/what-is-philosophy-index&quot;&gt;index page&lt;/a&gt; for “what is philosophy” you can find the concepts and questions that stood out for me. You can also find a list of people and works that are mentioned in the chapter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-chapter-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-chapter-1/</guid>
        
        <category>2021</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        <category>Ortega</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Start a new Country, a Review</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/4b711fa900291f491b0bdbb79f37342d.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cloud city by bioshock&quot; /&gt;
Cloud City from &lt;a href=&quot;https://bioshock.fandom.com/wiki/Columbia&quot;&gt;Bioshock Infinite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://balajis.com/about/&quot;&gt;Balaji Srivansan&lt;/a&gt;, a prominent figure in the blockchain space and one of the few to correctly predict (unfortunately) the sheer size and results of the COVID-19 pandemic, has been talking about the Network State for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, he published a post on 1729, about &lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/how-to-start-a-new-country/&quot;&gt;kickstarting a new Country&lt;/a&gt;, first on the cloud and then in the physical work. A fascinating concept, even more so because it doesn’t require any alien or very avant-garde technology, it just brings together existing technologies, synthesizing them in a new way. In the world of technology, we could say that he is proposing a new stack, like the LAMP stack for web servers, but for starting a country. Sounds like fun, a refreshing take in a thousand years old issue, but from the perspective of a technologist, an engineer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The promise of a new country is rather simple, a clean slate. A chance for old grievances to wither and die in the promise of a new world. Although Balaji doesn’t get into much detail on why we would want something like that, why we would want a new slate in the context of a country. 
From my perspective, the promise is to unite people who feel that the national identity no longer serves them. Not in the utilitarian sense, but rather that it doesn’t appropriately describe their identity in a meaningful way. There is a larger issue at hand here since cultural conditioning is far more powerful than we like to admit. It’s extremely hard to pill off assumptions and ideas that we think of as our own but in reality, they were given to us through our upbringing in a particular society and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, online communities have shown that people can meaningfully come together and create considerable value, while sharing a few of the attributes that are usually the crux of a country, such as a language, religion, and geographic location. The Internet has paved the way for a truly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_village&quot;&gt;global village&lt;/a&gt;. It’s interesting to think about notions such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-determination&quot;&gt;self-determination&lt;/a&gt;, in the context of an online community that shares certain characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of ways to start a new country, according to Balaji, from the usual suspects (e.g election, revolution, war) to more wacky ones (e.g space exploration). Cloud Countries is an interesting new concept, which takes the notion of an online community and adds a couple of missing layers to create the country stack. Although it starts online, the goal is to finally arrive at a point where that cloud country has application in the physical realm.  A number of geographical areas where people abide by the rules imposed by this cloud country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see the stack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system&quot;&gt;System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is akin to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_source&quot;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt; for software development. That means that is publicly auditable and anyone can raise issues or propose changes and improvements. We can think of it as the framework of a city-state in Ancient Greece, where almost everyone (excluding women and immigrants from other cities) participated in the commons. I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;internal-economy&quot;&gt;Internal Economy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centered around remote work. For now, that limits us to knowledge workers professions, but robotics could pioneer in translating the remote-work into physical existence. Although I am a huge proponent of remote work, working remotely all my professional life, Ι have my reservations about this. This would mean, essentially,  that building a robot with remote manual controls is considerably easier than creating the AI required to control such a robot. I can foresee construction workers in the form of robots, but I am not sure if the AI will take &lt;em&gt;that much&lt;/em&gt; to catch up so that it makes sense to work as a remote construction worker. Again, I have exactly zero experience in robotics and I haven’t really followed the space, so I might be completely off here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;culture&quot;&gt;Culture&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online, VR, and digital art. This I am buying. Seeing the meteoric rise and power of “memes” in pop culture, I can completely see a society where “Pepe” and the rest of the gang are as popular as BQQ on Sundays and dad jokes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;physical-realm&quot;&gt;Physical realm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of enclaves, sanctuary places that can range from apartments to whole buildings and acres of land. That again seems plausible, since embassies enjoy such privilege, but I can see sovereign countries fighting that, and why wouldn’t they. Imagine if anyone, at any point, could unilaterally say that their home is a sovereign entity and that slavery is OK in there. So, should anyone happen to be located there, the can’t be rescued by police or the army. If we are going to assume that every enclave, will also follow the laws and responsibilities of the nation state that it is located, I am not sure if we can really call it a sovereign entity. Sure, we can &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Live_action_role-playing_game&quot;&gt;LARP&lt;/a&gt; all we want, but unless we can self-determine in that physical space, there is no substance, other than that anyone who is part of the cloud country can couch-surf in my apartment because it’s part of that country. Balaji here mentions Bitcoin, but I think this analogy can be improved. Bitcoin can’t be assaulted by men with gun. An apartment can. Intrinsically they are not the same, so other countries must agree not to use force to exert power of that piece of land. Hell, nation states are being kept in balance due to a constant arms race around the world. Greece and Turkey is a good example, where a literally bankrupt country (Greece) with rampant corruption, is “forced” to spend a lot of money on defence, not only because of special interests but because of a real threat against it’s sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-define-a-country&quot;&gt;How to define a Country&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the article proceeds to talk about the definition of a country, where it talks about numerical definitions (land, population) and societal (UN recognition). In my view, a nation is nothing more than a group of people who have agreed to cooperate and function as a unit. That means that they agree to a set of rules that they assume will help them live better lives, with a subgroup of people responsible for enforcing those rules. Although again, I am no expert, I see the different countries (city-state, empires, nation-state) as the same entity that just agrees to cluster around different shared attributes and at different states. In the end, it’s just how a group of people acknowledge themselves as part of something bigger, being that Athens, Thebes, the Russian Empire, or the European Union.   Of course, the self-determination of a particular group is only a part of the story, by changing the definition, you can also change the power structure and which class (subgroup) of people enjoy what benefits. As far as the subject at hand is concerned, I think that if enough people say that donkeys fly, then for all that it matters, they fly. As George Orwell put it in 1984: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2_%2B_2_%3D_5&quot;&gt;2 + 2 = 5&lt;/a&gt;. What I mean by that, is that if enough people want to LARP in a cloud country, that could totally work, but that country would mostly resemble an order like the Masons, rather a country, as people’s main identity and obligation will be towards a sovereign country state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want an organization, let’s call it a country, where it’s the main source of responsibilities and benefits of certain people, that’s another story. I am not sure how online syndication can be translated into the physical world without the requirement of military defense against those who will want to exert force. Perhaps a powerful entity that can safeguard its sovereignty by threatening to return fire in the form of hacking could make sense. Simply put, if you harm or force my people on my ground, you get severely hacked to the point that essential infrastructure may not work. In other words, I can’t imagine nation-states respecting this sovereignty without fearing the repercussions of their actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be very interesting to see the actual proto-implementation of this idea, an online community that will be clustered around the goal of bootstrapping a country. Given the novelty of the Internet and technologies like blockchain, I think that it’s important to push our imagination beyond assumptions and the status quo of the last century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not envision a new kind of country? A new way of organizing ourselves, a new way of finding our tribe. In a world, where religion, geographic location, and language are not the center-pieces of our identity. Having a minimal &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/identity.html&quot;&gt;identity&lt;/a&gt; (in relation to that of the last century) could indeed be improve society as a whole, through improve decision-making and public discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-last-point-on-ethics&quot;&gt;A last point, on ethics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a strong believer in “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ttbook.org/interview/i-am-because-we-are-african-philosophy-ubuntu&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;”, or rather that if the whole of society is doing better, then everyone is better. In other words, there is merit in having a strong social net and subside the basic education and healthcare of everyone. Of course that means that those who earn more will pay more in order to subsidize those who don’t earn as much. I would be afraid of a future where the economic elite will cluster in communities, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elysium_(film)&quot;&gt;Elysium&lt;/a&gt; without caring to help those around them. The increased “winner takes all” effects of the future is indeed frightening, a global community of extremely rich, extremely poor and little in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History has shown, I think, that less deviation from the average produces a more high-quality standard of living for the community as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the nation-state, let’s say Greece, has invested considerably in me in various ways. From the most obvious, as having “free” education and “free” healthcare, to the non-obvious, by providing a safe and organized society, parks to play on, roads to drive in, etc. I am not sure how ethical it would be of me, to simply say that since I don’t identify that much as Greek, but rather a citizen of the world, I will stop paying my fair due to the state and simply move on. In other words, I am not sure if I have paid back all the things that modern Greek society and it’s organized form, the Government, has offered me thus far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;external-resources&quot;&gt;External Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to read more about this concept, here are a couple of resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chartercitiesinstitute.org/post/charter-cities-podcast-episode-15-a-city-in-the-cloud-with-balaji-srinivasan&quot;&gt;Charter Cities Podcast Episode 15: A City in the Cloud with Balaji Srinivasan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tim.blog/2021/03/24/balaji-srinivasan/&quot;&gt;Balaji Srinivasan on The Future of Bitcoin and Ethereum, How to Become Noncancelable, the Path to Personal Freedom and Wealth in a New World, the Changing Landscape of Warfare, and More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/how-to-start-a-new-country-review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/how-to-start-a-new-country-review/</guid>
        
        <category>2021</category>
        
        <category>1729</category>
        
        <category>society</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An introduction to Philosohpy by Jose Ortega y Gaset</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/5c/JoseOrtegayGasset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jose Y Ortega Gasset&quot; /&gt;
Jose Y Ortega Gasset&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-philosophy&quot;&gt;What is philosophy?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what is that “philosophy”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last years, particularly after the crisis of 2008, philosophy has come to the foreground, as a hobby and way to combat the hardships of life. Interestingly enough, philosophy has evolved to have a great number of meanings and it hardly carries the weight that it used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word itself originates from-where you would expect-Greece. Philosophia(φιλοσοφία) or the love of wisdom is the activity where one searches for the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we have narrowly defined the term in the modern ages, originally it was meant to touch every domain under the sun. From astronomy to the social sciences. It was simply the search for truth in matters that are important. In that sense, everybody philosophized, not only because everybody wants to know the truth about matters of everyday life, but because every man has that internal need to “know”. As Aristotle put it, men are condemned to suffer, because they need to know everything there is, in a futile attempt to find purpose, while their apparatus-the brain-is incapable of grasping the full meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ortega_y_Gasset#:~:text=For%20Ortega%20y%20Gasset%2C%20philosophy,essential%20reality%20of%20the%20universe.&quot;&gt;José Ortega y Gasset&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most famous contemporary philosophers, worked during the first half of the 20th century, made an attempt to answer that very question: What is Philosophy. Although he is mostly known for “Revolt of the Masses”, Ortega produced a great corpus of knowledge around philosophy and the nature of man and society. Son of a newspaper director, he wrote many essays but never any books, preferring instead giving lectures in the university of Madrid, where more than 2000 people whole flock to attend them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/What-Philosophy-Jos%C3%A9-Ortega-Gasset/dp/0393001261&quot;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; “What is Philosophy” is an attempt by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mildred_Adams&quot;&gt;Midred Adams&lt;/a&gt; to synthesize the eponymous lecture into a magnificent work. Ortega is a great lecturer, carefully weaving together poetic language and literally tools to stimulate the interest of the audience. As we will see in Chapter 1, he intentionally doesn’t want to give us answers, but rather help us retrace the path that he himself followed when contemplating this great question. We will circle with him around many different subjects, retracing his own philosophical journey. That way, we can get exposed to the same ideas and develop our own ideas, free of biases (at least overly explicit ones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-am-i-doing-this-exercise&quot;&gt;Why am I doing this exercise?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything started as these things usually start: with a conversation that spiralled out of the main subject. That business partner turned into a mentor, and we started discussing in a more consistent basis about abstract ideas and philosophical subjects, usually anchored around my life experiences. COVID-19 has been a gift in that regard, as it gave me plenty of time to invest in myself and stressors to force me to re-assess nearly everything that I hold dear. Although I am only that the start of that process, philosophy has played a key role in an effort to put things in perspective and understand what is important and what is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all that time in my hand, it was only natural to think about principles and desires that I took for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where “What is Philosophy” comes into play, as an introductory work, it has condensed centuries of philosophical progress. It’s a great place to start one’s own journey, as it lays the logical foundation for a concrete philosophical view of the world. Given that it’s a university class, it is carefully constructed to introduce the audience to many different philosophical views and thinkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;game-plan&quot;&gt;Game Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every week,  I will share a summary and key points of a chapter of the book. It will talk about the chapter itself, as also about my personal takeaways and insights. Finally, we will assemble a list of important questions that sprung from the book but remain unanswered. These are the questions that personally struck a chord and will lead me to see, in black and white, what is important and what is not. What are the &lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt; questions for me, personally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, I intend to keep track of external books and thinkers that Ortega mentions. If you consider this book (and every book for that matter), like the trunk, the books and intellectuals that are mentioned are the branches and leafs. I have found that the best books will leave me with a dozen people to search for and books to read on various subjects that are relevant to the one that I just read.
This is a new attempt tot writing and building something in public. I hope it brings consistency and commitment to a rather chaotic way of working, enable me to log interesting thoughts and perhaps give an idea or two to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading and please don’t hesitate to leave a comment below. A discussion is worth a thousand posts. Take care&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-intro/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/what-is-philosophy-intro/</guid>
        
        <category>2021</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Proof-of-habit</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(DRAFT/DISCLAIMER — This post is a submission to a competition on 1729.com. No prizes will be awarded for any submissions at this time. Learn more at 1729.com/decentralized-task-creation.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;habits&quot;&gt;Habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design better habits for yourself and earn BTC&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are creatures of habit, you and me and everyone else. It only makes sense, in an ever-changing and complex work, the mind simply can’t keep up with it. It needs habits to remove complexity from daily life, so it can focus it’s mental capacity on the things that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that respect, habits work a little bit like heuristics, rules of thumb that the brain works to make a great number of daily decisions, without again evaluating every possible attribute and outcome. When people run in a certain direction, chances are that you will run too. It’s safer to run first and then evaluate second, since chances are that people run for a good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is that not all heuristics are good and likewise, not all habits. A great number of them are created through roads that we seldom control, like smoking which is a combination of psychological habit and a chemical necessity for Nicotine. Junk food is the same, rending our dopamine system out of control, as the junk food makes us produce inordinate levels of dopamine. Salt &amp;amp; sugar were rare in our ancestral homes and thus the brain evolved to reward highly the consumption of those kinds of foods. It simply hasn’t evolved to cope with over-salty or over-sweet food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, a habit is no more than a system. A repetitive process that you do to achieve a certain goal. Although the goal can be long-term (e.g learn Javascript), if you focus on the system itself, the habit, you know you will reach the destination almost deterministically. Moreover, by focusing on your habits you are considerably happier. Instead of winning once (learn javascript), you win every day (spend 1 hour learning javascript). By changing your goal, not only you reach the same destination, but you do it in a more fulfilling way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S94ETUiMZwQ&quot;&gt;Westworld&lt;/a&gt;, it has a great analogy between humans and the robots, named “hosts”. If you take the sum of our habits, you will see that a lot of us live in loops, either pleasant or unpleasant, but in loops all the same. Every day, week, month, year has a low level of variance, performing the same tasks day-in, day-out, either positive (go to the gym) or negative (fight with my partner). By changing our habits, by changing our loop, we can effectively alter the entirety of our life, without having to come up with a grandiose life plan, which is both extremely hard and intimidating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can think of a habit as a 1% daily improvement. Over a year, it can have a huge difference. That’s math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/tiny-gains-graph-700x700.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/continuous-improvement&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start by focusing on Now, what systems I can implement Now that will have a positive effect in my life. The goals we will set are not about a destination, but it’s about a system. If we do it right, we do it mindfully, we can alleviate the stress of life, since we know that the systems we have implemented will take us to the destination that we want. Thus, we no longer have to daydream about an ideal future, we just have to focus on Now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-the-task&quot;&gt;So, what’s the task.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most influential books I have read on Habits, is no other by the “Atomic Habits”. It’s very easily digestible, science-informed and practical to the bone, the ideal combination for a beginner practitioner of habit design. The book gives an entire framework on how to introduce new habits and remove old ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the following and &lt;strong&gt;earn $300&lt;/strong&gt; in BTC:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;read the “Atomic Habits”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make a review about it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and implement it for 1 month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will keep a daily log of this process by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;logging habits (e.g workout)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;taking notes on what you like (or don’t like) and anything interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and share:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A post at the start, stating your habit goals, the systems that have implemented and how you plan to tackle known and unknown challenges. Stating &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; you want to start/stop each habit is a great way to be mindful of your choices.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A post at the end (or 2 by-weekly posts), where you publish the actual habit log and notes from your personal reflection. What you could improve, what worked and how you feel about this exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logging habits is a great way to visually see your progress and keep yourself accountable, but also note-taking will help you visualize your mental progress through the month.  Of-course, in case you don’t feel like sharing a certain habit, you can log it anonymously, but log it and share the progress all the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sharing-is-caring&quot;&gt;Sharing is caring&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing this exercise has a &lt;strong&gt;double benefit&lt;/strong&gt;, at first it’s a great personal commitment tool. The brain is hardwired to appear consistent to the outside world, so it will go an extra mile just to keep you on the track. Exactly the thing we need when doing something new which we can easily give up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second benefit is to show to the rest that it’s not so hard to break away from bad habits or to introduce positive change in our lives. Doing a daily run in the park is not so hard as we make it to be and certainly time is not an issue. It’s a matter of priorities, but that’s probably to be a whole task on it’s own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdhqcCkIrwTRsTSHbxqtj6qUQ_xScSg6jNYRssCjg-AfgHFoA/viewform?embedded=true&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;685&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot;&gt;Loading…&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/proof-of-habit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/proof-of-habit/</guid>
        
        <category>2021</category>
        
        <category>1729</category>
        
        <category>cryptocurrency</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Migrating from Nodebb to Discourse</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/hWeP9ld.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;migrating-from-nodebb-to-discourse&quot;&gt;Migrating from Nodebb to Discourse&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I note some interesting things that I discovered during the migration of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.netdata.cloud&quot;&gt;Netdata Community&lt;/a&gt; from Nodebb to Discourse. I encountered an interesting bug and I had to deviate a bit from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.discourse.org/t/importing-nodebb-mongodb-to-discourse/126553/11&quot;&gt;“official” instructions&lt;/a&gt;, thus I thought it would be interesting to write some notes and share them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Random stranger in the internet, I hope that this blog post saves you some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;some-background&quot;&gt;Some background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Netdata in early August, we had just released our forum, based on Nodebb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Nodebb creators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NodeBB is a next-generation discussion platform that utilizes web sockets for instant interactions and real-time notifications. NodeBB forums have many modern features out of the box such as social network integration and streaming discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The premise of a well-engineered product was proven true, as Nodebb is an extremely pleasant software to work with, offering a modern technological stack which is easily extensible and using npm to vendor it’s plugins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of that, the plugins can be installed without rebuilding the forum, meaning that you can swap them on-the-fly. Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason we chose to move out of Nodebb is that although the project is awesome and the community is vivid, it’s not as popular as Discourse. This translates to Discourse having a greater number of available plugins and themes. Our community quickly grew with new requirements that would be hard to accommodate with the existing tools at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, in order to bring the forums up to shape, there is more manual work and maintenance required in Nodebb than in Discourse. Which would have been great, since the choice of customization is really wonderful, but I am the only Developer Relations team member at the moment. Thus whatever development I need, I will do it myself, limiting considerably the time I can invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, as I have now spent considerable time in Discourse, while I do prefer some elements of NodeBB, such as the technology stack or the plugin system; Discourse as a whole offers much more control and options.** It’s simply more mature.**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, there is a reason while the grand majority of forums look identical nowadays, and the reason is that Discourse is hard to beat. (Although there are a couple of interesting options oriented more for SaaS  products, maybe in another blog post)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-migration&quot;&gt;The migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to migrate, the good folks at Discourse, with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.discourse.org/t/importing-nodebb-mongodb-to-discourse/126553/11&quot;&gt;help of the community&lt;/a&gt;, have released a migration tool which parses the MongoDB/Redis database of Nodebb and extracts what can be extracted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few gotchas which I learned the hard way. Let’s see them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You have to build Discourse from source. As it’s a great piece of monolithic software on Ruby, it’s not as trivial as one would have hoped.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;MacOS is not playing nice with Ruby, avoid to reduce unneeded complexity.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Go for Ubuntu (or an Ubuntu VM) and prepare to spend quite some time in order to setup everything.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In case of a hosted NodeBB, make sure that you request the &lt;strong&gt;entirety&lt;/strong&gt; of the dump from their support . I spent quite some time trying to figure out why the migration did not work and the reason was that I simply requested half the dump.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In case you encounter the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;don't know what to do with file, skipping&lt;/code&gt; error, it means that you are using a newer version of mongorestore which has a slightly  different syntax than the one that is shown in the migration instructions.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mongorestore -d &amp;lt;database_name&amp;gt; /directory&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This will restore the database in a newly created database called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;database_name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Make sure you change the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;nodebb.rb&lt;/code&gt; line concerning the connection to the MongoDB to include the database you defined above: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@client = adapter.new('mongodb://127.0.0.1:27017/&amp;lt;database_name&amp;gt;'')&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is possible that NodeBB has created some orphan posts or another bad state inside the database. These abnormalities can break the migration script, bringing the process to a halt. This is what happened to my case and it’s the crux of this blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-culprit-is-314&quot;&gt;The culprit is 3.14&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to get some bad states in the forum, meaning that some topics would be created they would be impossible to be retrieved after their creation, resulting to a 404 instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As there were already internal discussions about the migration from NodeBB to another platform, I did not spend time to pin down the issue, as it was very very intermittent and I had a myriad other things to look after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some time, I discovered that the reason for this was the keyword &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Raspberry pi&lt;/code&gt; in the topic name. Every time a topic name included that keyword, the whole topic would enter a bad state, with 404 every single time and manual deletion of the topic (or change of the topic name) as the only solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I did not elect to debug the issue any further. That was a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-found-it&quot;&gt;We found it!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After talking with the good folks at NodeBB for this migration, I informed them of the bug, in case they wanted to dig deeper to evaluate if this is a wider problem or specific to my instance. They were very happy to investigate, and indeed they found the culprit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They use a specific regex on their reverse proxy that checks for common file extensions that they don’t serve. One of these files is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.asp&lt;/code&gt; which without the ^ or $ qualifier can match with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raspberry pi&lt;/code&gt;. By updating their rules, they were able to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, even with finding the culprit, the bad states had been created inside the database and unknowingly to me, they would come back and haunt me during the migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-migration-1&quot;&gt;The migration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried to test the migration, the script was unable to perform the migration and would crash, consistently and without giving much information. With the help of some debugging “print” statements that I put in the script, I found that the script would crash in area of topics import.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, it fetches a list of topics, then it starts pulling each topic from the database, and for each topic it pulls all it’s posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s simple really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, to my disappointment, the script would crash when it it tried to pull the post of a particular topic, the one with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;raspberry pi&lt;/code&gt; keyword in it’s title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I tried to fetch the topic from the database, using MongoCLI, I was successful, but when I tried to fetch the first post of that particular topic, I couldn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bingo!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, for the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Raspberry pi&lt;/code&gt; topics, while the topic existed, the post did not, resulting in a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; return for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_id&lt;/code&gt; and the crashing of the whole script. In Nodebb, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;post_id&lt;/code&gt; of the first post of a topic, is the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mainPID&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the data structure of the bad topic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JSON&quot;&gt;{
    &quot;_id&quot;: ObjectId(&quot;5f621635d53e46aab957f13b&quot;),
    &quot;_key&quot;: &quot;topic:99&quot;,
    &quot;cid&quot;: 3,
    &quot;lastposttime&quot;: 1600263733946,
    &quot;mainPid&quot;: 0,
    &quot;postcount&quot;: 0,
    &quot;slug&quot;: &quot;99/monitor-pi-hole-and-a-raspberry-pi-with-netdata&quot;,
    &quot;tid&quot;: 99,
    &quot;timestamp&quot;: 1600263733946,
    &quot;title&quot;: &quot;Monitor Pi-hole (and a Raspberry Pi) with Netdata&quot;,
    &quot;uid&quot;: 3,
    &quot;viewcount&quot;: 2,
    &quot;thumb&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
    &quot;deleted&quot;: 1,
    &quot;deletedTimestamp&quot;: 1600263902138,
    &quot;deleterUid&quot;: 37,
    &quot;mergeIntoTid&quot;: 100,
    &quot;mergedTimestamp&quot;: 1600263902160,
    &quot;mergerUid&quot;: 37
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I knew the exact problem, I had to think of a quick solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the function in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mongo.rb&lt;/code&gt; that fetches the list of topics from MongoDB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-ruby highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;topics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;offset&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;page_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;topic_keys&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mongo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;find&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;_key: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'topics:tid'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;skip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;offset&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;limit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;page_size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;pluck&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;topic_keys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;topic_key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;topic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;topic_key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assumed that if I removed the particular topic from that list of available topics, even if it exists in the database, the script will not try to import it and thus the migration will succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db.objects.find({_key:&quot;topics:tid&quot;})&lt;/code&gt; which returned a large number of documents, like this one: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;{ &quot;_id&quot; : ObjectId(&quot;5fb48402d53e46aab9f70b07&quot;), &quot;_key&quot; : &quot;topics:tid&quot;, &quot;value&quot; : &quot;198&quot;, &quot;score&quot; : 1605665794715 }&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I needed to delete the document with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&quot;value&quot;:&quot;99&quot;&lt;/code&gt; by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;db.objects.remove({_key:&quot;topics:tid&quot;, &quot;value&quot;: &quot;99&quot;})&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;em&gt;voila&lt;/em&gt;, the migration script was able to progress normally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you are interested, you can find the database schema on the NodeBB &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.nodebb.org/development/database-structure/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps for the migration in a bite-sized format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Import mongodump into local instance of Mongo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build Discourse from source and setup the discourse instance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run script which exports data from mongo, transforms them and import them to PostgreSQL.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Export Discourse instance through the Admin panel and import it to the production server.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;In case you are using a Hosted version of Discourse, you will need to contact support in order to restore the uploaded backup.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make modifications and prepare forum for production use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last problem that I encountered during the migration was related with the profile pictures that the script tried to import. Apparently some were pulled from the Internet and used some special characters which the script could not parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/paretoprinciple.asp&quot;&gt;Pareto Principle&lt;/a&gt; of 80/20, I am pretty happy with a 80% of the perfect result by investing only the 20% of total effort. I simply &lt;em&gt;commented-out&lt;/em&gt; the profile picture functions and went on with my life, and the migration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this will result in a &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; user experience, as existing users will have to re-upload their profile pictures, the other option was not viable as I would have to understand what is the exact issue and change the script, possibly learning some Ruby in the process. I simply don’t have the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to creating the foundations of a Developer Relations program, I have to be ruthless with prioritization, something which I have not done particularly successfully. But, as it’s a process, I learn continuously, and thus I opted to go for the quick-and-dirty solution for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, what really matters is to improve the experience of the community as a whole, making sure that it grows steadily.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/Migrating-from-Nodebb-to-Discourse/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/Migrating-from-Nodebb-to-Discourse/</guid>
        
        <category>2020</category>
        
        <category>developer-relations</category>
        
        <category>tutorial</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Developer Relations and Community CRMs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://thumbs.dreamstime.com/b/isometric-desktop-connected-to-servers-database-blue-back-background-data-center-concept-based-design-131817082.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;community-crms&quot;&gt;Community CRMs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developer Relations is a relatively new field, having emerged in response to the intricate needs of a technical community. A technical community, as Mary Thenvgall underlines, is not simply a community that has gathered around a purpose (product). &lt;strong&gt;They are a group of people who actively help one another and create value for the community&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, a technical community has powerful network effects in play, hardly a surprise, considering that the word of mouth is one of the best advertisements in the tech industry. With community members interacting all the time, exchanging best practices and solving problems together, being on IRC, reddit or a proprietary forum, there must be a person to monitor and nurture such interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-a-community-crm&quot;&gt;What is a Community CRM&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CRM tool, or Customer Relations Management tool is a tool which 1) serves as the source of truth for the customer and 2) logs all interactions of the customer with the company. A community CRM tool is a very new breed of tools which focus on helping DevRels with their job, by:
1) Giving them an aggregate view of the community health. With charts and graphs, the Developer Relations team can observe how the community engagements change over time, how code contributions evolve and if the community is talking about a particular matter. The important aspect to consider is that &lt;strong&gt;we want a view of the community as a whole, across all platforms.&lt;/strong&gt;
2) Logging all the touch-points of the community members with the community. This is important for improving the quality of tactical decisions in regards to particular members. If the team wants to identify candidates for their beta-testing program, it’s best to start contacting the community members who are most active, in whatever activity one cares (e.g contributions, forum topics, etc.)
3) Aggregating data from numerous data sources. Communities rarely exist on a single platform, but usually they are isles of different communities, with a central island serving as the core. We need to be able to gather information across every isle (e.g GitHub, Discourse, Discord, etc.) and then combine the data points so that we get a singular view for each community member and the community as a whole. &lt;strong&gt;The merger of different digital identities which belong to the same physical person is the name of the game.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we are going over 2 tools that I have been using for the last months in Netdata while wearing my Community Manager hat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-netdata-community&quot;&gt;The Netdata Community&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before jumping into the matter at hand, let’s talk a little bit about the Netdata community to give you some context on where I stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Netdata started in 2016 as an open-source project and immediately joined the hype train, with the peak reaching around 2017-2018. Since then, the community has obeyed to the laws of gravity, normalizing into a much more stable kernel of community members and contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) The community mainly runs on GitHub (for now, more on that later), thus we need a tool to help us analyze the health there.
2) We just shipped our new forums, which will be the center of the community from now on. 
3) Engineers and thought leaders interact on twitter as well, thus we need to be able to analyze the interactions there as well. This is not a hard requirement, since our marketing handles the twitter account.
4) Currently I am leading a team of 1 in Developer Relations, thus we need something easy to setup, so we can initially focus on customer-facing activities and setting up the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-suitors&quot;&gt;The suitors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are 3 products that I personally know of and they are appropriate for the use-case of a technical community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) ShavannahHQ
2) OrbitHQ
3) Grimoire Labs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to start with 3) and say that I haven’t used it. It seems the more in-depth and robust tool of the 3 in terms of analysis of technical communities (particular open-source). It supports many many different data sources and it can produce a dashboard rife with detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dashboard.mautic.org/app/kibana&quot;&gt;Mauticon dashboard&lt;/a&gt; for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it’s pertinent to underline that Grimoire is more of an analytic tools rather a CRM. What this means basically is that it is focused on analyzing the community as a whole and bring every bit of information about it and it’s members. This comes in contrast with the other 2 tools, which although they can perform a similar functionality, they care deeply about logging the individual journey of each member, as any CRM would do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also seems excessive complex, at least for the stage of the Developer Relations program and the Netdata community. We want something much more agile, which will not require time to setup and learn and can be used, immediately to guide tactical decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I put Grimoire Labs for re-assessment in the next Quarter, and moved forwards with the other two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;there-can-be-only-one&quot;&gt;There can be only one&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or can it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point, I have used both tools, in parallel, since they are quite complimentary in certain aspects, and while they are in alpha, they are free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would imagine, that come billing time, we will have to make a choice, but for the near future, I intend to use both, depending on the kind of report or decision that I want to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In broad terms, Orbit and Savannah, although they seem similar, and for sure they share a large part of their functionality, they seem to have a different focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savannah is mainly focused on the inside, the internal community  and how members interact in it. Orbit on the other hand, is also interested in the activities of the community members outside of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orbit&quot;&gt;Orbit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://orbit.love/&quot;&gt;Orbit&lt;/a&gt; is actually an implementation of the eponymous community model that was pioneered by one of the co-founders, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dzello.com/about/during&quot;&gt;Josh Dzielak &lt;/a&gt; his time as VP of engineering in Keen.io and then when leading Developer relations at Algolia. It is a venture-backed startup, currently with only 3 people and they are rapidly implementing new features and integrations. Moreover, they have a very active slack channel where users offer feedback and chat with the developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project was open-sourced in 2019 and anyone can find the model and contribute on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/orbit-love/orbit-model&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Although we are not going to talk about the model itself, it’s worth mentioning that it diverges from the usual AAARRRP funnel. You can read more about their differences on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/orbit-love/orbit-model#orbit-and-funnel&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The product is based on the concept of feed, for both the entire community and on a per-member basis. You can see a live feed of all the activities that members do inside the community, activities which of-course depend on the data sources that you have added.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/eduh4aM.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially useful on a per-member basis, since it allows you to take optimal tactical decisions when interacting with that particular community member. For example, you can welcome them to the community, you can congratulate them for their first contribution or see that they have interacted a lot of times, thus you want to chat with them about your beta-testing program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://orbit.love/assets/images/hero-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I particularly like about Orbit is that it has this &lt;strong&gt;twitter integration&lt;/strong&gt;, thus it can correlate different accounts from GitHub and Twitter that belong to the same person. This is powerful, because it allows you to find influencers if they have interacted with both accounts with your community (e.g a RT and a GitHub issue) or if they have added their twitter account on the GitHub profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orbit cares a lot about the reach of the members, measuring their reach both in terms of twitter and in terms of GitHub followers, stars in projects, etc. On top of that, Orbit tries to gather information about their profile from the GitHub activity (e.g what languages does the user usually uses in projects/contributions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said above, this outward angle is unique to Orbit and I feel that it adds value to the table, as I want to know how many “important” people my community attracts. These rock-stars, if managed correctly, can offer a unique boost to any community and project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, orbit offers standard reporting regarding the community members, their activities and platform-specific (e.g contributions on GitHub). Reports feel a bit weird and for sure they are not the strong suite of Orbit. For example, in the following image, although I can see the aggregate number of contributions and the relative size in a per-week manner, it’s not very useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/sa7Gh15.png&quot; alt=&quot;Orbit contributions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would prefer to see for the total period, what is the percentage of contributions to each open-source repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orbit finally offers a great &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.orbit.love/reference#members-overview&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;], which means that you can use Orbit to extract information about your community and export the to your data-lake. This is particularly important in the situation where you have a company CRM like hubspot or Salesforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using Orbit, you can extract and aggregate the community information about every community member, which is actually a lot of information, which is more-or-less auto-detected thanks to the frictionless integrations that Orbit offers. Taking an example from the docs can be quite illuminating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JSON&quot;&gt;{
  &quot;id&quot;: &quot;48986&quot;,
  &quot;type&quot;: &quot;member&quot;,
  &quot;attributes&quot;: {
    &quot;activities_count&quot;: 299,
    &quot;avatar_url&quot;: &quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/1110162582143406080/vu7_kN8f.png&quot;,
    &quot;bio&quot;: &quot;Co-founder &amp;amp; CTO @OrbitModel - we're hiring! · advocate for dev advocates 🥑 · Rails · JAMstack · DevRel · he/him · #BlackLivesMatter&quot;,
    &quot;birthday&quot;: &quot;September 12&quot;,
    &quot;company&quot;: &quot;@orbit-love&quot;,
    &quot;created_at&quot;: &quot;2020-04-21T14:43:54.266Z&quot;,
    &quot;deleted_at&quot;: null,
    &quot;first_activity_occurred_at&quot;: &quot;2011-03-14T19:04:59.000Z&quot;,
    &quot;id&quot;: 48986,
    &quot;last_activity_occurred_at&quot;: &quot;2020-10-11T18:52:47.000Z&quot;,
    &quot;location&quot;: &quot;Paris, France&quot;,
    &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Josh Dzielak&quot;,
    &quot;orbit_level&quot;: 1,
    &quot;pronouns&quot;: &quot;He/him&quot;,
    &quot;reach&quot;: 8,
    &quot;shipping_address&quot;: &quot;1 Champs-Élysée; Paris, France 75001&quot;,
    &quot;slug&quot;: &quot;dzello&quot;,
    &quot;source&quot;: &quot;api&quot;,
    &quot;tag_list&quot;: [
      &quot;DevRel&quot;,
      &quot;Founder&quot;,
      &quot;Paris&quot;
    ],
    &quot;teammate&quot;: true,
    &quot;tshirt&quot;: &quot;M&quot;,
    &quot;updated_at&quot;: &quot;2020-10-22T16:15:09.572Z&quot;,
    &quot;url&quot;: &quot;https://orbit.love/&quot;,
    &quot;web_url&quot;: &quot;https://app.orbit.love/dzello/members/dzello&quot;,
    &quot;twitter&quot;: &quot;dzello&quot;,
    &quot;github&quot;: &quot;dzello&quot;,
    &quot;discourse&quot;: null,
    &quot;email&quot;: &quot;josh@orbit.love&quot;,
    &quot;devto&quot;: &quot;dzello&quot;,
    &quot;linkedin&quot;: &quot;in/dzello&quot;,
    &quot;love&quot;: 13.886322317666968
  },
  &quot;relationships&quot;: {
    &quot;identities&quot;: {
      &quot;data&quot;: [
        {
          &quot;id&quot;: &quot;149721&quot;,
          &quot;type&quot;: &quot;email_identity&quot;
        },
        {
          &quot;id&quot;: &quot;173894&quot;,
          &quot;type&quot;: &quot;twitter_identity&quot;
        },
        {
          &quot;id&quot;: &quot;376&quot;,
          &quot;type&quot;: &quot;github_identity&quot;
        },
        {
          &quot;id&quot;: &quot;608267&quot;,
          &quot;type&quot;: &quot;devto_identity&quot;
        },
        {
          &quot;id&quot;: &quot;609227&quot;,
          &quot;type&quot;: &quot;linkedin_identity&quot;
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can extract all the members that exist inside Orbit, take what information is relevant for your use-case and import that information inside the company CRM. You can even store them in your data-lake and enrich any user information with their community standing in a very frictionless manner. Quite neat I should say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This integrations work the other way around too. You can export product data from your production database and into the data-lake, then for each community member you have, you can create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/code&gt; which is a simple text associated with the community member and visible inside their Orbit profile. This Note could be a simple generated text that contains information about their product use, like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;plan: standard
Number of machines: 16
Last login: 22-11-2020
Usage: very active
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives you valuable context in your interactions with the community members, since you know how they have interacted with the product, how credible their feedback is, etc. To super-charge this integration, a SSO system for your forum and main product would ensure that people don’t use different emails, thus making impossible to correlate their identities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the orbit framework, it is certainly useful that the tools offers an abstraction to the Community Manager in regards to community member segmentation. It is an easy and quick way to understand how the community is evolving and get a quick understanding of a member’s identity inside the community, either by viewing their &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;reach&lt;/code&gt; , their &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;love&lt;/code&gt; (total engagement) or their &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;orbit level&lt;/code&gt;. As a professional, I think I would prefer to be able to customize the point system of my platform, as I feel that for each community, the same activities could have different points so that the model is more reflective of the community reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in my twitter community, there is a member which is depicted as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Orbit 1&lt;/code&gt; or inner community, but I would even hesitate to call them a community member. The reason is that they are a media account talking about the Greek Startup ecosystem. They have simply mentioned Netdata a lot of times, either in the context of funding announcements, hiring or simply as a greek startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I would probably reduce the impact a tweet can have in considering a user part of my community. Although I am sure that there is a rationale behind the point system, which might be appropriate for more cases, offering the choice seems like a low-hanging fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can join the beta-testing and the slack channel, by visiting &lt;a href=&quot;https://orbit.love&quot;&gt;Orbit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-sources&quot;&gt;Data sources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.orbit.love/docs/setup-the-orbit-discourse-integration&quot;&gt;Discourse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.orbit.love/docs/setup-the-twitter-integration&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.orbit.love/docs/how-to-setup-the-orbit-github-integration&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zapier.com/apps/orbit/integrations&quot;&gt;Zapier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.orbit.love/reference&quot;&gt;API integration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;savannah&quot;&gt;Savannah&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savannah is the brainchild of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/mhall119/&quot;&gt;Michael Hall&lt;/a&gt;, Senior Community Manager at InfluxDB. I met Michael, during his time in the Linux Foundation, when I was an active member of the EdgeX Foundry community in my IoT years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met Michael again in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://devrelcollective.fun/&quot;&gt;DevRel collective&lt;/a&gt; slack and he was kind enough to invite me for a closed beta of SavannahHQ, a community CRM for Developer Relations, by a Developer Relations guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Savannah offers a great aggregate view of the various aspects of my community, integrating the Graphs inside the dashboard (in contrast with Orbit which are isolated). For some reason, this offers a greater user experience, with the product feeling much more coherent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, taking the contributions example from Orbit, in Savannah I can view the number of total contributions for the period and then a contribution-by-channel pie chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/ZHsER8t.png&quot; alt=&quot;Savannah Contributions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information is the same, but in Savannah is more thoughtfully presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, Savannah does a functional division of the community in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conversations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Contributions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It offers a view of the community for each function, both in terms of the aggregate, but also in terms of distinct community members. For example, in the image bellow, we see the total number of conversations in the Netdata community, we see conversations by Tag (keyword-based) but also we see a list of community members, based on activity, engagement, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/fCMeBS0.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;strong&gt;one of the most interesting features&lt;/strong&gt; of SavannahHQ is the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;connections&lt;/code&gt; tab, which shows the community as a graph, where each community member is a node and each edge is a connection between 2 community members. A connection is defined as the interaction of 2 community members on some platform at some point in their community journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://docs.savannahhq.com/insights/connections/LooseWeb.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As this feature is somewhat complex, meaning that it is just a visualization, and demands experience to properly decode the patterns and shapes that you see, it’s best to visit the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.savannahhq.com/insights/connections/&quot;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt; and read how different shapes can signify different things about the health of the community. It’s a great start and I can’t wait to see this feature evolve by giving the user &lt;strong&gt;actionable insights&lt;/strong&gt; about their community, without demanding excessive experience from their part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-words-1&quot;&gt;Final Words&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SavannahHQ is a one-man band project and it shows, it’s much more immature than orbit, with a number of features missing from the package, such as a robust &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; API to be able to extract all this info from the platform and to a proprietary data warehouse or to enrich the central CRM of your company. Moreover, there are a number of features here and there, that are currently missing and are implemented as we speak. For example, Savannah offers a historical view of the community that goes up to 6 months in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the positive side, because it’s a one-man band with a small slack community, feedback is integrated in a rapid manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, as you have probably guessed, it does not provide a data visualization like the live feed in Orbit, for neither the aggregate or in a per-member basis. It has a list of all the conversations in the member’s profile, but I would argue that is not very useful. Furthermore, it doesn’t concern itself with things such as reach, as it only focuses on the interactions that the community members are having inside the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can join the beta-testing, learn more about the product and join the slack in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.savannahhq.com/&quot;&gt;Savannah CRM docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-sources-1&quot;&gt;Data Sources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discourse&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gitlab&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RSS feed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blog&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discord&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API integration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I have yet to make a final decision on which tool is more appropriate for my needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded to use Savannah for more aggregate understanding of my community, being able to quickly see who are my latest contributors or the most active in conversations. Moreover, the network graph is a great tool to see how the community is evolving and to spot community members which start to become more active, get more connections and becoming a link for the community. Finally, the keyword tag of conversations is a nice little feature, as it gives me a gist of the conversations that are happening, in broad terms of-course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I use Orbit to get a live understanding of my community, see the newest contributors and make sure to welcome them to the community and thank them for their contributions. Moreover, being able to monitor twitter is a great aspect, as I can see the &lt;em&gt;high reach&lt;/em&gt; individuals that interact with Netdata and keep an eye on them, without having to use yet another service/platform. Finally, the reports offer a great detailed view of the community as a whole and being able to quickly benchmark the current period of the last one, is a great asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this seems a new and exciting field, I intend to come back with thoughts and insights from my experience. At this moment, I am trying to standardize a process around  these tools, and hopefully I will be able to share back and open-source my results in a timely manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, community is everything.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/developer-relations-and-community-crms/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/developer-relations-and-community-crms/</guid>
        
        <category>2020</category>
        
        <category>developer-relations</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A powerful heuristic: The Lindy Effect</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/0WFM8IA.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Intro Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping a blog is more demanding than I anticipated, nowadays it captures a good chunk of my weekend as it requires considerable effort to write and edit. Although at times, it’s quite tempting to reduce the frequency of posts, I suspect that I am not quite ready yet to produce less frequent but more demanding work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I would like to reiterate a mental-model that I discovered a while back and since then it has proved it’s value numerous times in my everyday life. It’s called the lindy effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lindy effect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered this model during my Incerto times. &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/34qn8yU&quot;&gt;Incerto&lt;/a&gt; is a book series written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nassim_Nicholas_Taleb&quot;&gt;Nassim Nicholas Taleb&lt;/a&gt; and it deals about a whole range of subjects, mainly centered around probability and randomness, from a practical, a philosophical, a mathematical and an ethics perspective. It is considered one of the most valuable modern-day books and truly, I plan to revisit them soon, as they are considerably dense in ideas and knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Lindy effect is named after a famous cafe in New York, called…Lindy. It simply states that for some things, their life expectancy is proportional to their current age. If they are 100 years old, they probably will be around for another 100 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The observant reader will have already guessed that automatically all living things are non-lindy compatible, as they have an organic life expectancy which is not determined by their age. On the other hand, a book (not the actual book, but the ideas in it) is lindy compatible. Seneca-a favorite of mine-lived during the times of the Ancient Roman republic, dying at 65 AD. His essays have been around for close to 2000 years and are still popular amongst millions of people, from adepts of stoicism to simple everyday folks. We can safely assume that his letters will be around for another 2000 years, given that climate change does not end civilization as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, it’s a very intuitive and easy to understand concept, as you are probably using it as a heuristic for decision making, albeit to your ignorance. I would say that it’s especially apparent to cultures which modernity has not changed much and which have a long historical continuity, such as the greek. My parents, which are in their 60s, would often cite “folk wisdom”, small quotes that dictate how we should behave and act in everyday life. They are not akin to religious doctrines, as they don’t speak from an angle of ethics, but rather from a practical point of view. As I read more and more about mental models and psychology, I see that this folk wisdom is the practical equivalent of knowledge that has resurfaced after experiments in various fields, such as social psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I remember my mother saying since I was a little: “we judge others, from ourselves”. This is of course free translation from greek and it speaks about the paradigm and how our actions and thoughts shape the very lens from which we view the world. We judge the world around us based on our personal experience, thus when we take advice we should always have in mind the context in which this advice was formulated, in other words the life of the person giving that piece of advice. Another example, is the saying “show me your friends and I’ll tell you who you are”, which of course refers to how our friendships and personal relationships shape the very essence of our existence. Relationships act as feedback loops that can be either positive or negative, as we are social “animals” and we seek the affirmation of others in order to decide on what’s right and wrong. Relevant to this, I think, is the fact that most people who want to go and live in places like San Francisco, are mainly interested in the network and the high density of ridiculously audacious people, rather the city itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these ideas are of course Lindy compatible and will exist for thousands more years, with or without scientific research backing them up, because they are simply the distilled wisdom of hundreds of generations. People first encountered these “universal truths” through experience, and people who followed these doctrines were more successful in the societal genetic pool. Thus, society as a whole filtered hundreds of “sayings” through countless generations and only a handful survived in the gene pool. This process, albeit slow, has created a set of doctrines which have passed the ultimate challenge of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lindy effect is a powerful heuristic, and can easily be applied in our everyday lives. When I was looking for a new gym in Athens, I had a large number of options with more or less the same characteristics. But, knowing the lindy effect, I tried a little experiment. Of all of those, I chose the gym which was the smallest and oldest. My assumption was simple: if a small gym has managed to stay afloat in the economic crisis, and they have managed to do so for a lot of years (taking into consideration the life expectancy of the average gym), I assumed that it is a good gym. Quickly I found out that my assumption was correct and a small team of passionate professionals had managed to compete with gyms that were times of magnitude larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same can be applied for anything, from an idea, to books and friendships. The Lindy effect is a powerful concept that we should try to have at the back of our head when we want to quickly decide on a choice. The only caveat being that the options that we evaluate are Lindy compatible and that we don’t treat Lindy as a maxim. It only tells what is probably going to happen, not what will happen. If an idea has been around for thousands of years, sure it must be robust against time (which is the harshest of critics), but that doesn’t mean that an outlier event can’t wipe it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always have in mind (and that’s a maxim), that our world is too complex for us to comprehend, thus we should be prepared for anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading 🙇‍♂️&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/the-lindy-effect/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/the-lindy-effect/</guid>
        
        <category>2020</category>
        
        <category>decision-making</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From the Greek University to a startup -  Part 4 [GR]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/DO1aj5n.png&quot; alt=&quot;intro image&quot; /&gt;
Image: We start as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Otgm8oxEy_w&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, but we want to become &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vm4tx1O9GAc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;κριτήρια-επιλογής-εταιρείας&quot;&gt;Κριτήρια επιλογής εταιρείας&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Σε αντίθεση με αυτό που πιστεύουν οι περισσότεροι απόφοιτοι, στην πραγματικότητα επιλέγουμε την  πρώτη μας εταιρεία όπως και αυτή επιλέγει εμάς. Έχοντας ένα γεμάτο βιογραφικό και εξερευνώντας όλες τις επιλογές μας (π.χ remote), μας δίνετε η ευκαιρία να έχουμε μια πληθώρα επιλογών. Εδώ φυσικά τίθεται το ερώτημα των φίλτρων που θα εφαρμόσουμε για να επιλέξουμε την καταλληλότερη επιλογή.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media3.giphy.com/media/YwpylUojkfOZa/giphy.gif?cid=ecf05e47riaox3s0ycatcq5y7r2b2h39yxzciw0skio7tw1v&amp;amp;rid=giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Συχνά λένε πως το πρώτο “αφεντικό” αποτελεί και την πιο σημαντική επιλογή μας σε όλη την καριέρα, καθώς θα έχει τεράστια επιρροή στις εργασιακές συνήθειες που θα αναπτύξουμε. Η σωστή κουλτούρα και καθοδήγηση μπορούν να επιταχύνουν την επαγγελματική μας ανάπτυξη σε μοναδικό ρυθμό, όπως αντίστοιχα και να αποτελέσουν και τροχοπέδη σε περίπτωση που δεν έχουν ανάλογη εμπειρία ή δεν τους ενδιαφέρει η ανάπτυξη των εργαζομένων.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Don’t pick a job. Pick a Boss. Your first boss is the biggest factor in your career success. A boss who doesn’t trust you won’t give you opportunities to grow.” - &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Raduchel&quot;&gt;William Raduchel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Όπως λένε και στο χωριό μου (που δεν έχω 🥺) , με όποιον δάσκαλο καθίσεις, τέτοια γράμματα θα μάθεις.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Μετά, θέλουμε να επιλέξουμε μια εταιρεία που βρίσκεται σε μια ανερχόμενη αγορά που αναπτύσσεται συνεχώς, έτσι οι πιθανότητες της επιτυχίας της εταιρείας θα είναι αυξημένες.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αυτό θας μας επιτρέψει αφενός να μάθουμε έναν καινοτόμο τεχνολογικό χώρο και αφετέρου ελαχιστοποιεί το ρίσκο μιας κακής οικονομικής έκβασης (συνήθως οι startups δίνουν μετοχές ως κομμάτι της αμοιβής –  &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-gr&quot;&gt;skin in the game&lt;/a&gt;, remember?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Τέλος, κοιτάμε μια εταιρεία που μας αρέσει το προϊόν, καθώς το πάθος για το αντικείμενο ενασχόλησης θα φανεί στην δουλειά μας. Εκτός αυτού, η δουλειά αναμένεται να είναι ιδιαίτερα απαιτητική, με ωράρια που δυνητικά να ξεπερνούν το 8ωρο, άρα είναι θεμιτό να ξοδεύουμε το μεγαλύτερο μέρος της ημέρας μας σε κάτι που μας ευχαριστεί.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media1.giphy.com/media/KcDreBsNBhGVrXYWAr/giphy.gif?cid=ecf05e47e7kybg8szghlqlgsyrfu64q9ikz6cj6fjce94j0f&amp;amp;rid=giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Κάπου εδώ θα πρέπει να παρατηρήσουμε ότι δεν έχω αναφέρει καθόλου τον &lt;strong&gt;ρόλο&lt;/strong&gt;. Αυτό γιατί αρχικά δεν πρέπει να μας ενδιαφέρει και πολύ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στις startups οι ρόλοι είναι αρκετά ευμετάβλητοι και ασαφώς ορισμένοι, έτσι υπάρχει μεγάλη κινητικότητα και είναι εύκολο να κινηθούμε προς τον ρόλο και τις ασχολίες που μας ενδιαφέρουν.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Είναι καλό να έχουμε στο πίσω μέρος του μυαλού μας πως είναι πιο δύσκολο να “μπούμε” σε έναν οργανισμό που να αξίζει (με βάση τα κριτήρια παραπάνω), παρά να κατευθυνθούμε προς τον ρόλο που μας ενδιαφέρει.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Στις startups οι ρόλοι είναι αρκετά ευμετάβλητοι και ασαφώς ορισμένοι, έτσι υπάρχει μεγάλη κινητικότητα και είναι εύκολο να κινηθούμε προς τον ρόλο και τις ασχολίες που μας ενδιαφέρουν.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;και-τώρα-τι&quot;&gt;Και τώρα τι;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Καθώς τελειώνεις τις σπουδές, έρχεται σιγά σιγά η ώρα του επόμενου βήματος, για πρώτη φορά στην ζωή σου έχεις την απόλυτη επιλογή, να ασχοληθείς με οτιδήποτε θες.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Οι πανελλαδικές είναι 50% ανεπηρέαστη επιλογή, συχνά και 0%, yup it sucks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το πιο σύνηθες λάθος είναι να κάνουμε ένα μεταπτυχιακό γιατί δεν έχουμε κάποια καλύτερη ιδέα.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Είναι λογικό να θέλουμε να αποφύγουμε την δυσκολία της απόφασης, συνεχίζοντας να κάνουμε το μόνο που ξέρουμε να κάνουμε καλά, δηλαδή να σπουδάζουμε, όμως δυστυχώς δεν θα μας οδηγήσει στην προσωπικη και καθημερινή ευτυχία.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Πολύ απλά, εαν δεν ξέρουμε τώρα την απόφαση, δεν υπάρχει λόγος να την ξέρουμε σε ένα χρόνο από τώρα. Ειδικά εαν κάνουμε ακριβώς το ίδιο με αυτό που κάνουμε τώρα (απλά με διαφορετική ύλη).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Άρα, πρέπει να κρίνουμε το μεταπτυχιακό ως μια επαγγελματική απόφαση, δηλαδή ως προς την επένδυση σε χρόνο και χρήμα σε σχέση με αυτά που θα προσλάβουμε (και αν τελικά τα χρειαζόμαστε/θέλουμε).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Για παράδειγμα, αν και σκεφτόμουν σοβαρά το μεταπτυχιακό σε ένα συγκεκριμένο εργαστήριο του εξωτερικού, μια τρομερά μοναδική εμπειρία, ήξερα πως θέλω να καταλήξω στο χώρο των startups. Καθώς αυτός ο χώρος δεν απαιτεί &lt;em&gt;μπεζ χαρτιά&lt;/em&gt;, έκρινα πως η εργασιακή εμπειρία σε μια εταιρεία ανάλογης ποιότητας, θα μου έδινε περισσότερα εφόδια.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kαθώς τελειώνουμε και αναλογιζόμαστε το επόμενο βήμα στην αγορά εργασίας, για να ξεκαθαρίσουμε στο μυαλό μας τι θέλουμε, μπορούμε να προσπαθήσουμε να απαντήσουμε στις ακόλουθες ερωτήσεις:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Τι είναι αυτό που σου αρέσει  να κάνεις;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Τι είναι αυτό που κάνεις καλά;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Σε τι μπορείς να φέρεις αξία;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Χαρακτηριστικά εταιρείας που θα θέλουμε να δουλέψουμε ( π.χ remote, startup, tech, IoT, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ουσιαστικά, θέλουμε να σκεφτούμε λίγο πιο συνειδητά, πράγματα που έχουμε ήδη σκεφτεί έμμεσα. Να βρούμε κάτι που μας ευχαριστεί, στο οποίο είμαστε καλοί (ή μπορούμε να γίνουμε) και φυσικά κάτι που δημιουργεί αξία. Ως αξία, μπορούμε να σκεφτούμε μια υπηρεσία ή αντικείμενο για το οποίο, κάποιος, κάπου, θα πλήρωνε. (π.χ ένα τραγούδι, ένα κέικ, ένα πρόγραμμα λογισμικού, κλπ.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Έχοντας γράψει τις σκέψεις μας, είναι η ώρα να χρησιμοποιήσουμε το δίκτυο μας (έχουμε μιλήσει για αυτό στο &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part2-gr/&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;), δηλαδή να ζητήσουμε την βοήθεια ανθρώπων με εμπειρία, που έχουν μια πιο πλήρη εικόνα της πραγματικότητας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μπορούμε να επικοινωνήσουμε με όλους και να ζητήσουμε μια σύντομη συνάντηση, μια κουβέντα. Θυμήσου πως όλοι θέλουν να βοηθήσουν ένα νέο απόφοιτο, ειδικά εάν χρειάζεται απλά μια μικρή βοήθεια στην κατεύθυνση ώστε να κεφαλαιοποιήσει την σκληρή εργασία που έχει ήδη κάνει.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Όλοι κάποτε βρέθηκαν στην θέση σου, και θέλουν να σε βοηθήσουν γιατί και εκείνους κάποιος τους βοήθησε τα πρώτα τους βήματα (ή θα ήθελαν να τους έχει βοηθήσει). &lt;strong&gt;Καλό είναι να συνεχίσεις και εσύ την παράδοση στο μέλλον.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;κάμερα-σε-εμένα&quot;&gt;Κάμερα σε εμένα&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://luben.tv/wp-content/uploads/2016/09/kamerasemena.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Τελειώνοντας το πανεπιστήμιο, κατέληξα πως ήθελα να δουλέψω στο κομμάτι του product management (ομπρέλα διαφορετικών ρόλων) και ύστερα από μια ανάλυση των ευκαιριών που είχα άμεσα, έβαλα τους 2 πρώτους στόχους (εταιρείες).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Για να μπορέσω να κάνω αυτή την μετάβαση, από το πτυχίο του μηχανικού στις &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2017/12/what-it-takes-to-become-a-great-product-manager&quot;&gt;δεξιότητες&lt;/a&gt; του product manager, πέρασα ένα διάστημα όπου μελετούσα με φρενήρης ρυθμούς (τεκμήριο εργατικότητας κατά την διάρκεια των συνεντεύξεων που έκανα μετά), ωστέ να αποκτήσω τις βασικές γνώσεις-θεμέλια.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στην πρώτη εταιρεία,  η διπλωματική, σε συνδυασμό με υπόλοιπο βιογραφικό, μου επέτρεψε να περάσω γρήγορα τα στάδια των συνεντεύξεων και να έχω το πολυπόθητο offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Συγκεκριμένα, η διπλωματική ήταν τεκμήριο ότι έχω κάποιες τεχνικές γνώσεις και βαθιά κατανόηση του προϊόντος τους, καθώς αυτό αποτελεί μέρος της λύσης που παρουσίαζα σε αυτή.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Η διπλωματική, όπως αναφέρω και στο &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part3-gr/&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, μπορεί να αποτελέσει χρυσό εισιτήριο εαν την χειριστούμε έξυπνα.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Οι &lt;strong&gt;μικρές&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;startups&lt;/strong&gt; (&amp;lt;150 άτομα) που βρίσκονται σε στάδιο &lt;em&gt;ραγδαίας&lt;/em&gt; ανάπτυξης, &lt;strong&gt;σπάνια παίρνουν άτομα με μικρή ή χωρίς εμπειρία&lt;/strong&gt;. Αυτό γιατί, λόγω των λίγων ατόμων και των τεράστιων απαιτήσεων, έχουν ανάγκη από έναν πυρήνα έμπειρων ανθρώπων.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στην δεύτερη εταιρεία, για να δημιουργήσω τις κατάλληλες προϋποθέσεις, κινήθηκα πάλι με βάση όσα έχω ήδη αναφέρει. Έτυχε να γνωρίσω τον ιδρυτή, και μέσα από την συζήτηση μας προσπάθησα αφενός να καταλάβω τι να περιμένω στην εταιρεία, και αφετέρου τι ψάχνουν στους υποψήφιους.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Κάθε startup έχει κάποια κουλτούρα, που συνήθως ξεκινάει από τους ιδρυτές.  Αξίζει λοιπόν να βρούμε ομιλίες ή συνεντεύξεις τους και να καταλάβουμε τι είδους άτομα ψάχνουν. Με αυτόν τον τρόπο, θα μπορούμε να τονίσουμε σχετικές πτυχές του ιστορικού/χαρακτήρα μας κατά την διάρκεια της συνέντευξης.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Καθώς εδώ δεν είχα την διπλωματική (για αυτούς το θέμα μου ήταν άσχετο), έπρεπε να αποδείξω με διαφορετικό τρόπο πως γνωρίζω το προϊόν και να δείξω διάθεση για συνεισφορά (το αναφέραμε στο &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-gr/&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Περιληπτικά,  το προσέγγισα κάπως έτσι:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Βελτιώσεις στο &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tutorialspoint.com/programming_methodologies/programming_methodologies_program_documentation.htm&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; (τεκμήριο κατανόησης του πως δουλεύει το προιον και πως βελτιώνουμε την εμπειρία του χρήστη)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ανάπτυξη επέκτασης για το πρόγραμμα-προϊόν (τεκμήριο κατανόησης του πως δουλεύει το προιον)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Δημιουργία content (blog post) σχετικά με την εγκατάσταση του προγράμματος και την χρήση του σε πραγματικές συνθήκες (Τεκμήριο δυνατότητας συγγραφής κειμένου)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Εγκατάσταση και χρήση του προγράμματος σε πραγματικές συνθήκες (ουσιαστικά έπεισα έναν επαγγελματία γνωστό μου να το εγκαταστήσει και να το χρησιμοποιήσει)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Τεκμήριο οτι μπορώ να πείσω κάποιον για τα πλεονεκτήματα του προϊόντος&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Τεκμήριο οτι θα κάνω το “κάτι παραπάνω” με σκοπό να μάθω αυτό που θέλω&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Πήρα ιδέες για το τι μπορεί να θέλουν οι χρήστες, πως μπορεί να γίνει καλύτερο το προϊόν - συνήθεις ερωτήσεις στις συνεντεύξεις.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Έρευνα αγοράς για να κατανοήσω καλύτερα τους ανταγωνιστές και την αγορά. Απέκτησα έτσι κατανόηση για τον χρήστη, του προβλήματος που λύνει, των ανταγωνιστών, την κατεύθυνση που πιθανώς να πηγαίνει το προϊόν. (Χρήσιμο για την συνέντευξη)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ψεύτικη συνέντευξη με άτομο από το δίκτυο μου. Με βοήθησε στο να καταλάβω ποιά είναι τα σημεία του βιογραφικού που είναι σχετικά με την θέση και πως να απαντήσω σε standard ερωτήσεις που έχουν να κάνουν με τον ρόλο.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Η παραπάνω δουλειά οδήγησε άτομο από το δίκτυο μου να με προτείνει στην εταιρεία.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αν και δεν είχε προσωπική επαγγελματική εμπειρία μαζί μου, τα παραπάνω αποτέλεσαν τα τεκμήρια που ήθελε να δεί για να κάνει την σύσταση (και να “ρισκάρει” το όνομα του).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Εάν θέλουμε να μας συστήσει κάποιο άτομο από το δίκτυο μας, πρέπει να φροντίσουμε να κάνουμε πρώτα το κομμάτι μας, να αποδείξουμε τις δεξιότητες μας και την διάθεση για σκληρή δουλειά. &lt;strong&gt;Κανείς δεν θέλει να κάνει μια κακή σύσταση.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;το-αποτέλεσμα&quot;&gt;Το Αποτέλεσμα&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στην δεύτερη εταιρεία η πρόσληψη δεν προχώρησε καθώς χρειάζονταν άτομα με εμπειρία στην συγκεκριμένη φάση, έτσι ξεκίνησα στην πρώτη εταιρεία, η οποία αποτελεί και μια από τις καλύτερες εμπειρίες που είχα ποτέ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Δούλεψα για μερικούς μήνες, όπου και αποφάσισα να μεταπηδήσω στην δεύτερη όταν μου δόθηκε η ευκαιρία.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το ενδιαφέρον είναι ότι η ευκαιρία μου δόθηκε την δεύτερη φορά, λόγω της επιμονής μου (και των νέων αναγκών τις εταιρείας). Η συνεισφορά που έκανα στο πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα ήταν υποτυπώδης και το βιογραφικό μου δεν είχε κάτι το εξεζητημένο (με μόλις μερικούς μήνες εμπειρίας).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Δεν είναι ανάγκη να είμαστε ιδιαίτερα χαρισματικοί ή έξυπνοι.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Είναι λίγο κλισέ, αλλά &lt;strong&gt;η σκληρή δουλειά κερδίζει την ευφυΐα, κάθε φορά&lt;/strong&gt;. Όπως αντίστοιχα η εκτέλεση (execution) μιας ιδέας σε πρακτικό επίπεδο, δηλαδή πως τρέχεις μια startup, είναι πιο σημαντική από την μοναδικότητα της ιδέας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hard work beats talent when talent fails to work hard.”
― &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Durant&quot;&gt;Kevin Durant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Οπότε, αν βρούμε μια εταιρεία που θέλουμε πολύ να δουλέψουμε, που θεωρούμε πως έχει να μας δώσει πολλά, μας αρέσει το αντικείμενο και ο τομέας, τότε ίσως να αρκεί να κάνουμε μόνο 1 πράγμα.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Να το διεκδικήσουμε με κάθε τρόπο που μπορούμε.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στέλνουμε στους εργαζόμενους και τους ρωτάμε για την εμπειρία τους. Δημιουργούμε αξία με κάθε τρόπο (π.χ κώδικα, blog post) και δείχνουμε τις δεξιότητες που έχουμε. Εξελισσόμαστε σε ενεργό μέλος της κοινότητας και βοηθάμε άλλους μέσα σε αυτήν.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το πιο σημαντικό όμως είναι &lt;strong&gt;να προσπαθήσετε πολλές φορές&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μπορεί την πρώτη φορά να μην προχωρήσει, όμως δεν σημαίνει πως θα απορριφθούμε και την επόμενη φορά.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αφενός, ποτέ δεν ξέρουμε τις εσωτερικές ανάγκες κάθε εταιρείας (αλλάζουν πολύ συχνά) και αφετέρου η επιμονή δείχνει από μόνη της κάτι. Είναι μάλιστα πιθανό να το εκτιμήσουν περισσότερο από έναν υποψήφιο με “καλύτερο” βιογραφικό, γιατί δείχνει πως είμαστε εργατικοί, δεν τα παρατάμε, επιμένουμε και πιστεύουμε στον εαυτό μας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ε-και&quot;&gt;Ε και;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Κάπου εδώ, ίσως αναρωτιέται κάποιος γιατί να ξοδεύουμε τόσο σκέψη και ενέργεια στην επιλογή του εργασιακού περιβάλλοντος, οπότε ας ξανά κάνω μια μικρή αναφορά.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Η δουλειά, μπορεί να μην αποτελεί την μοναδική πτυχή της ζωής σου, όμως αποτελεί την δραστηριότητα που σου αποσπά 8+ ώρες κάθε μέρα.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ακόμα, μέσα από την δουλειά μας, μπορούμε να βοηθήσουμε άλλους ανθρώπους, μπορούμε να συμβάλουμε για ένα σκοπό που είναι σημαντικός για εμάς, να χαρούμε την ευτυχία της δημιουργίας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ίσως να αξίζει λίγο παραπάνω προσπάθεια για να έχουμε μια καθημερινότητα η οποία μας ευχαριστεί, οπού ξυπνάμε κάθε μέρα με όρεξη, μας παθιάζει και &lt;strong&gt;δυνητικά&lt;/strong&gt; κυριολεκτικά μας &lt;strong&gt;νοηματοδοτεί&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Work gives you meaning and purpose, and life is empty without it – Stephen Hawking (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20180314-stephen-hawkings-advice-for-a-fulfilling-career#:~:text=Work%20gives%20you%20meaning%20and,empty%20without%20it%20%E2%80%93%20Stephen%20Hawking&amp;amp;text=One%20of%20the%20pieces%20of,life%20is%20empty%20without%20it.%E2%80%9D&quot;&gt;πηγή&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Η δημιουργία αξίας και η θετική συνεισφορά στην κοινωνία (με οποιοδήποτε τρόπο), οδηγεί σε μια πιο &lt;a href=&quot;https://greatergood.berkeley.edu/article/item/5_ways_giving_is_good_for_you&quot;&gt;χαρούμενη ζωή&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Δεν υπάρχει λόγος να περιορίζουμε τον εαυτό μας στις ελεύθερες ώρες και να μην ευχαριστιόμαστε όλες τις ώρες που είμαστε ξύπνιοι.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;δε-εντ&quot;&gt;Δε εντ;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Διαβάζοντας ξανά και ξανά τα κείμενα αυτά, είμαι χαρούμενος που αποτύπωσα σε χαρτί (έστω σε οθόνη) όσα σκεφτόμουν και έζησα τον τελευταίο χρόνο. Αν και είμαι μόλις στην αρχή, ήταν μια ενδιαφέρουσα (και σίγουρα δύσκολη) μετάβαση, η οποία μπορώ να πω πως έγινε με επιτυχία.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Η αποτύπωση τους με βοηθάει να θυμηθώ τι έχω καταφέρει, και παράλληλα να παραμένω γειωμένος στο έδαφος, καθώς αναλογίζομαι το πόσο τυχερός έχω υπάρξει.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Έτσι, το να μοιραστώ 3-4 πράγματα που έμαθα με τον δύσκολο τρόπο και να γλιτώσω πιθανώς κάποιον από το να σπαταλήσει χρόνο, απλά το κάνει καλύτερο.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The wise man learns from the mistakes of others -Otto Von Bismarck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Παράλληλα, ήταν καλό που έκανα μια μικρή παύση και ανασκόπησα όσα έχουν συμβεί τον τελευταίο χρόνο. Ζώντας μιας ζωή με φρενήρης ρυθμούς, συχνά ξεχνάμε να γιορτάσουμε τις νίκες μας, αλλά προτιμάμε να εστιάζουμε στις ήττες, όσο λίγες ή ανούσιες και αν πιθανώς είναι.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μάλιστα, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.idonethis.com/negativity-bias/&quot;&gt;έρευνες&lt;/a&gt; έχουν δείξει πως το μυαλό μας τείνει να δίνει μεγαλύτερη σημασία στα αρνητικά γεγονότα από οτι στα θετικά. Έτσι, όσο όμορφη και αν είναι η ζωή μας, εάν δεν γιορτάζουμε τις νίκες αλλά μένουμε στις ήττες μας, θα είμαστε δυστυχισμένοι.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Γι’αυτό, νιώθω ευγνώμων για όσα έχουν συμβεί μέχρι τώρα. Από τους ανθρώπους που γνώρισα, στις ευκαιρίες που εμφανίστηκαν και τις συμπτώσεις που υπήρξαν.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Καλώς η κακώς, χρειάζεται και τύχη και σκληρή δουλειά για να πετύχουμε.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Σε ένα κόσμο τόσο σύνθετο όσο τον δικό μας, η τύχη πάντα θα παίζει ρόλο. Πολύ απλά, δεν μπορούμε να αντιληφθούμε τον τρόπο που λειτουργεί ο κόσμος. Ένα μαύρο κουτί, που εμείς βλέπουμε μόνο τι βάζουμε εμείς και τι βγάζει αυτό.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Οτιδήποτε δεν μπορούμε να επαναλάβουμε, πολλές φορές με συνεπή αποτελέσματα, είναι πολύ πιθανό να είναι αποτέλεσμα της τύχης και όχι των δικών μας δεξιοτήτων.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Από την επόμενη εβδομάδα θα αρχίσω να γράφω επιτέλους λίγο πιο τυχαία: από οικονομικά, έως startups και φιλοσοφία, ίσως και την θεά τύχη (lady fortuna).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Έως τότε, σας ευχαριστώ για την ανάγνωση 🙇‍♂️&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-gr&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part2-gr&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part3-gr&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part4-gr&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part4-gr/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part4-gr/</guid>
        
        <category>2020</category>
        
        <category>self-improvement</category>
        
        <category>career</category>
        
        <category>greek</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From the Greek University to a startup -  Part 3 [GR]</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/8qIBK8s.png&quot; alt=&quot;intro image&quot; /&gt;
Image: We start as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Otgm8oxEy_w&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, but we want to become &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vm4tx1O9GAc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;πρακτικά---η-δική-μου-εμπειρία&quot;&gt;Πρακτικά - Η δική μου εμπειρία&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στα δύο προηγούμενα μέρη (&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-gr&quot;&gt;Μέρος 1ο&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-startup-part2-gr&quot;&gt;Μέρος 2ο&lt;/a&gt;) μιλήσαμε σχετικά με την αξία της εμπειρίας σε μια καινοτόμα startup, κάποιες πιθανές προκλήσεις που θα εμφανιστούν και φυσικά τι μπορούμε να κάνουμε για να προετοιμαστούμε καλύτερα.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στο τρίτο και τέταρτο μέρος, σκέφτηκα να μοιραστώ τα βήματα που έκανα μέχρι τώρα και με τα οποία ανακάλυψα σκουντουφλώντας, όπως όταν ξυπνάμε μέσα στην νύχτα για μια επιδρομή στο ψυγείο του σπιτιού.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Πιθανώς να επαναλάβω κάποια από αυτά που έχω αναφέρει, ελπίζω να το ανεχτείτε. 🤷‍♂️&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;η-πάτρα&quot;&gt;Η Πάτρα&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το 2014 εισάγομαι στο τμήμα ΗΜ&amp;amp;ΤΗ στην Πάτρα, και το πρώτο έτος το πέρασα όπως το περνάει ο κάθε φοιτητής που σέβεται τον εαυτό του, με μια ξέφρενη νυχτερινή. Μέσα σε μια χρονιά κατάληψης, η ζωή μου μπορώ να πω οτί ήταν ευχάριστη, καθώς αποτελούνταν κυρίως απο video games και εξόδους, ενώ ήταν και η πρώτη φορά που ζούσα μόνος μου. Ολα τέλεια δηλαδή.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://4.bp.blogspot.com/-as7yCQzMZg0/UwpA2BC8RCI/AAAAAAAACkU/ruGHVZFo5o8/s1600/patrpanta.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Εντελώς τυχαία, προς το τέλος της χρονιάς, συμμετέχω σε μια εκδήλωση που έπρεπε να σχηματίσεις μια ομάδα και να δημιουργήσεις μια startup μέσα σε ένα ΣΚ. Με λίγα λόγια, είχες 2 ημέρες να βρεις (εσύ και η ομάδα σου) ένα πρόβλημα, να επιβεβαιώσετε πως υπάρχει και να βρεις μια βιώσιμη λύση.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=50Mx_cxtpZM&quot;&gt;Startup Weekend Patras 2014&lt;/a&gt; είναι το γεγονός που μου άλλαξε κυριολεκτικά την ζωή, όσο αστείο και cheesy και αν ακούγεται. Ο λόγος είναι απλός. Ήταν η πρώτη φορά που δημιούργησα κάτι από το μηδέν, που βρήκα λύση για ένα υπαρκτό πρόβλημα και αντιμετώπισα πραγματικές προκλήσεις.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αν και το συναίσθημα της δημιουργίας είναι σίγουρα &lt;strong&gt;εθιστικό&lt;/strong&gt;, το πιο σημαντικό πράγμα που κερδίσαμε εκείνη την ημέρα, ήταν η κατανόηση ότι γίνεται ένα άτομο στα 18 του να λύσει ένα υπαρκτό πρόβλημα που αντιμετωπίζουν 10, 100, 1000 άνθρωποι.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μάλιστα ανακαλύψαμε και για πρώτη φορά την δύναμη του διαδικτύου, καθώς μέσα σε ένα ΣΚ, καταφέραμε να μάθουμε για δεκάδες διαφορετικά θέματα, από design έως business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Εκείνη την στιγμή ήταν που κατάλαβα οτι αυτό ήθελα να κάνω για την υπόλοιπη ζωή μου. Να λύνω υπαρκτά προβλήματα, σε υπαρκτές και πραγματικές συνθήκες (όχι π.χ σε εργαστήριο) και γιατί όχι, να ζω από αυτό. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mindspace&quot;&gt;Mindspace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Τον επόμενο χρόνο, αποφασίσαμε με ένα φίλο, να ξεκινήσουμε το &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindspace.gr&quot;&gt;Mindspace&lt;/a&gt; στην Πάτρα, έναν σύλλογο από φοιτητές και αποφοίτους τότε, με σκοπό να γνωρίσουμε στους φοιτητές την κουλτούρα της επιχειρηματικότητας/startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Βασικός άξονας ήταν να παρουσιάσουμε αφενός μια διαφορετική οδό από την κλασική &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;πανεπιστήμιο -&amp;gt; εταιρεία&lt;/code&gt; και αφετέρου να φέρουμε σε επαφή ανθρώπους επιχειρηματίες που μπορούν να αποτελέσουν πρότυπα.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Εαν θέλετε να μάθετε για το startup οικοσύστημα στην Πάτρα, προτείνω να διαβάσετε αυτό το άρθρο στο &lt;a href=&quot;https://startupper.gr/news/60360/prepi-na-klonopiisoume-tin-patra-parafta/&quot;&gt;Startupper.gr&lt;/a&gt; από τον Γιώργο Κουρκουτά.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Όμως, τι κερδίζει κάποιος μέσα από αυτή την προσπάθεια που αργότερα εξελίχθηκε σε μια ομάδα 10+ ατόμων;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Αναπτύσσει οργανωτικές δεξιότητες (κυρίως γύρω από την διαχείριση του χρόνου του)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Αναπτύσσει ηγετικές δεξιότητες&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Αποκτάς γνώσεις γύρω από τον χώρο που με ενδιαφέρει επαγγελματικά, δηλαδή γύρω από την καινοτόμα επιχειρηματικότητα (startups)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Αναπτύσσει δεξιότητες σχετικά με την παρουσίαση και την δημόσια ομιλία&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Δημιουργεί εκτεταμένο δίκτυο από ανθρώπους που με ενδιαφέρουν, δηλαδή εργαζόμενους και ιδρυτές σε startups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Αποκτά τεκμήρια για χαρακτηριστικά του χαρακτήρα του (π.χ πρωτοβουλία, οργάνωση, πειθαρχία, κλπ.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το να είσαι μέρος σε μια ομάδα , σου δίνει την δυνατότητα να δεις δια ζώσης πως είναι να συνεργάζεσαι υπό πίεση με άλλα άτομα προς την επίτευξη ενός κοινού σκοπού.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ακόμα, μπορείς να δοκιμάσεις οργανωτικές μεθοδολογίες (πχ. scrum) και να αποκτήσεις πρακτική εμπειρία, συμπληρώνοντας τις τεχνολογικές σου γνώσεις με τις επαγγελματικές δεξιότητες που απαιτούνται.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ακόμα και το πιο απλό, δηλαδή πως να γράψω ένα email το οποίοι είναι: 1) εύκολο στν ανάγνωση, 2) εύκολο στην κατανόηση και 3) δεν κουράζει, είναι μια τέχνη που την έμαθα από την ενασχόληση μου στο Mindspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glados&quot;&gt;GLaDOS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Παράλληλα, στο δεύτερο έτος κατάλαβα οτί δεν έχω ιδέα από προγραμματισμό, και επειδή υποτίθεται πως σπούδαζα υπολογιστές, είπα να το διορθώσω. Αν και η σχολή μου προσέφερε ερεθίσματα (από τις λίγες φορές), ο προγραμματισμός εν γένει απαιτεί προσωπική ενασχόληση και πολλές ώρες “πτήσης”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Είπα έτσι, να μάθω προγραμματισμό και να φτιάξω ένα έξυπνο σπίτι στην πορεία, ως ένα &lt;em&gt;τεχνητό&lt;/em&gt; στόχο για να εξασκήσω αυτά που μαθαίνω. Όμως, καθώς ήθελα παράλληλα να φτιάξω ένα portfolio, δημοσίευσα το πρότζεκτ σε ένα φοιτητικό συνέδριο, το έβαλα στο github και το παρουσίασα σε ένα συνέδριο ανοικτού κώδικα. Φυσικά, αυτό δεν το έκανα με την μια, αλλά προέκυψε μέσα από συζητήσεις με άτομα του χώρου, μέσα απο πειραματισμό και ακολουθώντας το mantra “γιατί όχι;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Για να μάθεις περισσότερα για τα πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα, μπορείς να διαβάσεις αυτό το &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcsteps.gr/192308-%CF%80%CF%81%CE%BF%CE%B3%CF%81%CE%AC%CE%BC%CE%BC%CE%B1%CF%84%CE%B1-%CE%B1%CE%BD%CE%BF%CE%B9%CE%BA%CF%84%CE%BF%CF%8D-%CE%BA%CF%8E%CE%B4%CE%B9%CE%BA%CE%B1-open-source/&quot;&gt;άρθρο&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το ενδιαφέρον είναι ότι αν και το πρότζεκτ έχει περιορισμένη τεχνολογική αξία, δηλαδή δεν είναι καινοτόμο ή σύνθετο, αποτέλεσε μια εξαιρετική ευκαιρία να μάθω διάφορες τεχνολογίες. Την ίδια στιγμή εμφανίστηκε ως μια εξαιρετική δικαιολογία για να εξασκηθώ στην δημόσια ομιλία και να αποβάλλω (λίγο δυστυχώς) το στρες που την συνοδεύει.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Το πρότζεκτ το ονόμασα GlADOS (reference anyone?) και περισσότερες πληροφορίες μπορείτε να βρείτε &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1LHQ19l1VnQlL7C01QMgR19Y691zYDgHe/view&quot;&gt;εδώ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Δεν είναι ανάγκη να σκεφτούμε μια πολύ καλή ιδέα, &lt;em&gt;ούτε καν καλή&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μόνο η υλοποίηση, το &lt;strong&gt;“χτίσιμο”&lt;/strong&gt; δηλαδή ενός “πράγματος”, θα μας οδηγήσει στο να αποκτήσουμε πρακτικές γνώσεις γύρω από αυτό.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μάλιστα, αν μας ευχαριστεί η διαδικασία και η μάθηση, θα το κάνουμε και καλά. Εάν το κάνουμε καλά, σίγουρα θα υπάρχουν άνθρωποι, είτε στο διαδίκτυο, είτε στην κοινότητα μας, που θα θέλουν να μάθουν για αυτό.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Όμως, έστω πως έχω ένα τεχνολογικό πρότζεκτ. &lt;strong&gt;Γιατί να μπω στην διαδικασία να το μοιραστώ μέσα από το Github;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ανεβάζοντας τον κώδικα και την παρουσίαση στο github, υπάρχουν τεκμήρια για τις τεχνικές μας γνώσεις&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Η μορφή του πρότζεκτ (πρόβλημα-λύση) υποδηλώνει οτι δεν έχουμε στενά τεχνολογική σκέψη, αλλά αντιλαμβανόμαστε το γενικότερο πρόβλημα&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Η δημοσίευση της εργασίας, η παρουσίαση και ο κώδικας αποδεικνύουν ότι μας ενδιαφέρει να μοιραζόμαστε και να βοηθάμε άλλους μέσα από αυτά που μαθαίνεις.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Έχουμε την ικανότητα και την πειθαρχία/όρεξη να μάθεις για διάφορα τεχνολογικά θέματα, όπως ηλεκτρονική, προγραμματισμός ενσωματωμένων, προγραμματισμός διαδικτύου,  κλπ. .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Πάντα θα υπάρχουν ευκαιρίες για να παρουσιάσουμε κάτι, πάντα θα υπάρχουν άνθρωποι που ενδιαφέρονται να ακούσουν για αυτό που γνωρίζουμε. Αρκεί να τις ψάξουμε ✌️&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το καλύτερο που έχουμε να κάνουμε, είναι να σκεφτούμε τι δεξιότητες θέλουμε να αναπτύξουμε (ή τι γνώσεις να αποκτήσουμε),και μετά να βρούμε δραστηριότητες που μας ευχαριστούν και μας προσφέρουν αυτή την γνώση.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;το-τέλος-έρχεται-επιτέλους&quot;&gt;Το τέλος έρχεται (επιτέλους)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Τελειώνοντας την σχολή, έπρεπε να κάνω την διπλωματική μου και ήξερα πως δεν είχα αναπτύξει αρκετά τις γνώσεις μου γύρω από την τεχνολογία, τουλάχιστον αρκετά για να μπορώ να πω ότι είμαι μηχανικός.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Είχα όμως ένα ακόμα χαρτί (ή αγγαρεία, ανάλογα πως το δείς 😅), την &lt;em&gt;διπλωματική μου εργασία&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Η διπλωματική ή πτυχιακή, είναι μια πολύ καλή ευκαιρία να ασχοληθείς με ένα τομέα που σε ενδιαφέρει και να το χρησιμοποιήσεις ως τεκμήριο για την πρώτη σου δουλειά. Γνωρίζοντας τον τομέα που σε ενδιαφέρει, αποφάσισε-&lt;em&gt;περίπου&lt;/em&gt;-τον ρόλο που θέλεις και δες τι τεχνολογίες ζητάνε. &lt;strong&gt;Χτίσε την διπλωματική σου γύρω από αυτό&lt;/strong&gt;, αποκτώντας γνώσεις και &lt;strong&gt;πρακτική&lt;/strong&gt; εμπειρία σε ένα κομμάτι δουλειάς που το κάνεις έτσι και αλλιώς για να αποκτήσεις το πτυχίο.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/wnoEutjol5ei4/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Για την διπλωματική μου, αποφάσισα πως ήθελα να είναι κυρίως συνδυασμός τεχνολογιών, με μικρό ερευνητικό κομμάτι και μεγάλη έμφαση σε τεχνολογίες αιχμής (π.χ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/resources/what-container&quot;&gt;docker containers&lt;/a&gt;) και σε πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα (π.χ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edgexfoundry.org/&quot;&gt;EdgeX Foundry&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://balena.io&quot;&gt;balena&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Έχω λοιπόν αποφασίσει την θεματική, έχω σκεφτεί την προσέγγιση. Τι λείπει;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αυτός που θα αναλάμβανε την εργασία μου και ο ερευνητής που θα με συμβούλευε στην πρακτική της υλοποίηση. Προσέγγισα λοιπόν, ένα συγκεκριμένο ερευνητή, που γνώριζα πως αφενός ασχολείται με τεχνολογίες αιχμής, αφετέρου θα μου δώσει την ελευθερία που ήθελα στο να ασχοληθώ με αυτά που με ενδιαφέρουν. Αν και ήδη είχα ξεκινήσει να κάνω έρευνα σε κάτι συναφές με τον κ. Γιαλελή, ανακάλυψα πως αυτή η νέα στόχευση της διπλωματικής μου με ενδιέφερε περισσότερο, και άρα χρειαζόταν ένας διαφορετικός υπεύθυνος.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το ωραίο με την πρακτική ενασχόληση είναι οτί σου επιτρέπει συνεχώς να αλλάζεις την ρότα σου, κρατώντας πάντα τις επιλογές σου ανοικτές και διαλέγοντας την πιο συμφέρουσα με βάση τις πληροφορίες που έχεις. &lt;strong&gt;Ακόμα και η λάθος επιλογή, σου δίνει μια πληροφορία που δεν είχες πριν&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ότι και να γίνει, κερδίζεις.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Χάνεις μόνο όταν δεν δρας, αλλά προσπαθείς, στάσιμος, να αποφασίσεις την βέλτιστη οδό.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Και φυσικά, αυτό είναι αδύνατο.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αξίζει εδώ να κάνω μια μικρή αναφορά στον καθηγητή μου κ. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/spyros-denazis-03366b2/&quot;&gt;Δενάζη&lt;/a&gt; και στον ερευνητή (και φίλο πλέον) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/christostranoris/?originalSubdomain=gr&quot;&gt;Χρήστο Τρανόρη&lt;/a&gt;, που όχι μόνο με δέχτηκαν στην ερευνητική τους ομάδα, αλλά με βοήθησαν να προσανατολιστώ μέσα στον δαιδαλώδες τεχνολογικό θέμα που επέλεξα και να συγκεκριμενοποιήσω τις ιδέες μου προς κάτι που μπορεί να υλοποιηθεί και είναι ερευνητικά ενδιαφέρον.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αυτή η ερευνητική ομάδα είναι και η ομάδα που υλοποιεί ένα από τα πρώτα δίκτυα 5G στην Ευρώπη, στο Πανεπιστήμιο της Πάτρας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;το-ίδιο-μοτίβο-και-με-την-διπλωματική&quot;&gt;Το ίδιο μοτίβο και με την διπλωματική&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μέσα από τα πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα, είχα την ευκαιρία να ασχοληθώ με project που έχουν αξία στην πραγματική ζωή (δεν αποτελούν δηλαδή στενά ερευνητικά project) και να γνωρίσω από κοντά το τρόπο με τον οποίο λειτουργούν αυτές οι κοινότητες.  Φυσικά και εδώ, εφάρμοσα το μοτίβο που περιέγραψα παραπάνω:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ανέβασα την διπλωματική μου στο &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/odys-thesis-rg&quot;&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt; και την διαμοίρασα στο επαγγελματικό μου κοινωνικό δίκτυο&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ανέβασα τον κώδικα στο &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/odys-thesis&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Έγραψα την διπλωματική με τέτοιο τρόπο ώστε το κομμάτι της υλοποίησης να είναι σε μορφή &lt;em&gt;οδηγού&lt;/em&gt;, ωστέ να μπορεί κάποιος να ακολουθήσει τα βήματα και δυνητικά να χτίσει πάνω σε αυτά&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Προσπάθησα να διατυπώσω ένα πραγματικό πρόβλημα και να θέσω την διπλωματική μέσα σε πραγματικές καταστάσεις. Προσέγγισα ένα γενικότερο πρόβλημα (αν και επιφανειακά) και όχι στενά μια τεχνολογική εφαρμογή.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Ιδανικά προσπάθησε να συμμετέχεις σε πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα, συνεισφέροντας όσο μπορείς (σε κώδικα, documentation, παραδείγματα, blog-posts, κλπ. ). Εκτός του ότι βοηθάς ένα πρότζεκτ ανοικτού κώδικα, συμμετέχεις σε μια ενεργή κοινότητα, δικτυώνεσαι και αναπτύσσεις σχετικές δεξιότητες (τεχνολογικές και μη).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Τελειώνοντας λοιπόν την διπλωματική και παίρνοντας αυτό το πολυπόθητο μπεζ χαρτί, ήρθα αμέσως αντιμέτωπος με την ανεύρεση εργασίας.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Μάλιστα, η πρόκληση ήταν πιο επείγουσα από ποτέ, γιατί μέχρι να βρω εργασία και να είμαι ανεξάρτητος οικονομικά, έπρεπε να μείνω στο πατρικό μου. Όποιος έχει μείνει μόνος του λόγω σπουδών γνωρίζει πως αυτή η λύση είναι ελαφρώς λιγότερο επίπονη από το να φύγεις στα καράβια.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/3t7RAFhu75Wwg/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Fun Fact: Η σχολή βγαίνει πολύ πιο αναίμακτα και σχεδόν εύκολα, όταν αποφασίσεις για ποιό λόγο ακριβώς θέλεις να την τελειώσεις. Έναν λόγο συγκεκριμένο και βαθιά προσωπικό. Το να πάρεις ένα χαρτί ή επειδή σε έστειλαν οι γονείς σου, δυστυχώς δεν μετράει. Όσο δεν αποφασίζεις για ποιό λόγο κάνεις όλο αυτό το μαρτύριο, τότε και μαρτύριο θα παραμένει, και κακά θα το κάνεις (άρα θα κρατήσει και περισσότερο). Δεν έχει να κάνει με τον χρόνο που αφιερώνεις στο διάβασμα, αλλά με τον τρόπο (και την διάθεση).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Νομίζω πως σύντομα θα γράψω την ταπεινή μου γνώμη για την αξία του πανεπιστημίου, ή την έλλειψη της τέλος πάντων. Έχω δει πολλά παιδιά στην ηλικία μου να κοπανιούνται με μια σχολή που δεν τους αρέσει, χάνοντας τα πιο δημιουργικά και όμορφα χρόνια. Υπό την πίεση μιας κοινωνίας που αρνείται να εκσυγχρονιστεί και να αφήσει τα παιδιά της να ανακαλύψουν τον κόσμο ακολουθώντας την περιέργεια τους, διαβάζοντας και εμβαθύνοντας στα θέματα που τους ενδιαφέρουν.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Όταν μια μεγάλη πλειονότητα των φοιτητών βελτιστοποιούν τις σπουδές τους με άξονα την ευκολία (π.χ επιλογή εύκολων μαθημάτων, κλπ.) και όχι με άξονα το ενδιαφέρον τους ή αποτελέσματος των σπουδών (γνώσεις, εμπειρία, κλπ.), τότε κάτι πάει πολύ στραβά.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Το ξέρω, γιατί και εγώ έτσι έδρασα. Όμως, μην ξεφεύγουμε, θα κάνω &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=diss&quot;&gt;diss&lt;/a&gt; μια άλλη φορά.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Στο επόμενο και (ελπίζω) τελευταίο μέρος, θέλω να μοιραστώ το τελευταίο στάδιο αυτής της πορείας, που δεν είναι άλλο από την μετάβαση από την φοιτητική πραγματικότητα σε αυτή των startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Πως κατάφερα να κερδίσω μια θέση σε 2/2 εταιρείες που κυνήγησα;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Αν και θα σας κάνω σπόιλερ, θα σας πω.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ήμουν κατά βάση τυχερός.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ευχαριστώ για την ανάγνωση.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-gr&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part2-gr&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part3-gr&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part4-gr&quot;&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>https://odyslam.com/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part3-gr/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://odyslam.com/blog/from-greek-uni-to-startup-part3-gr/</guid>
        
        <category>2020</category>
        
        <category>self-improvement</category>
        
        <category>career</category>
        
        <category>greek</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
